<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Security on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/security/</link><description>Recent content in Security on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 07:26:05 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/security/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The AI Security Crisis You Can't Ignore: Why Simon Willison's 'Lethal Trifecta' Demands Immediate Action</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/27/the-ai-security-crisis-you-cant-ignore-why-simon-willisons-lethal-trifecta-demands-immediate-action/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 07:26:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/27/the-ai-security-crisis-you-cant-ignore-why-simon-willisons-lethal-trifecta-demands-immediate-action/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems creating a perfect storm for data theft? Security researcher &lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/16/the-lethal-trifecta/"&gt;Simon Willison&amp;rsquo;s recent analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals a chilling reality: AI agents combining three specific capabilities create what he calls the &amp;ldquo;lethal trifecta&amp;rdquo; – a combination so dangerous that attackers can easily trick systems into accessing private data and sending it directly to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-three-components-that-spell-disaster"&gt;The Three Components That Spell Disaster&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willison identifies three seemingly innocent AI capabilities that, when combined, become a security nightmare:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>AI Safety vs. Security: The Critical Distinction Your Organization Can't Afford to Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/26/ai-safety-vs-security-the-critical-distinction-your-organization-cant-afford-to-ignore/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 10:21:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/26/ai-safety-vs-security-the-critical-distinction-your-organization-cant-afford-to-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you treating &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/ai-safety"&gt;AI safety&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/security-101/what-is-ai-for-cybersecurity"&gt;AI security&lt;/a&gt; as the same thing? If so, your organization might be missing critical vulnerabilities that could compromise both your operations and compliance posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-dangerous-misconception"&gt;The Dangerous Misconception&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many languages use the same word for both concepts, &lt;a href="https://oecd.ai/en/wonk/when-it-comes-to-ai-incidents-safety-and-security-are-not-the-same"&gt;the OECD emphasizes that AI safety and security are distinct yet interconnected domains&lt;/a&gt; that require different approaches and frameworks. This distinction isn&amp;rsquo;t just academic - it has real implications for how you protect your organization.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Guardrails Just Got Outsmarted by Emojis: The Semantic Prompt Injection Crisis</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems as secure as you think? Recent research from &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s AI Red Team&lt;/a&gt; reveals a concerning reality: attackers can now bypass some AI guardrails using something as simple as emoji sequences and visual symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-invisible-threat-in-plain-sight"&gt;The Invisible Threat in Plain Sight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/cyberpedia/what-is-a-prompt-injection-attack"&gt;Semantic prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; represent an emerging frontier in adversarial attacks against AI systems. Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/prompt-injection"&gt;prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; that rely on text manipulation, these attacks use symbolic visual inputs - emoji-like sequences, rebus puzzles, and other visual representations - to potentially compromise &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; while evading some detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Embeddings as Secure as You Think?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:49:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your organization&amp;rsquo;s AI embeddings are protecting sensitive information? A groundbreaking new research paper reveals a troubling reality: what you thought was secure data representation might be an open book to determined attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are AI embeddings?&lt;/strong&gt; For readers new to this concept, &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ai/what-are-embeddings/"&gt;embeddings are numerical representations&lt;/a&gt; that convert complex data like text, images, or audio into mathematical vectors that AI systems can process. Think of them as a way to translate human-readable information into a language that machines understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Team Ready for AI? Why Education Must Come Before Implementation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 08:35:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: your organization just invested in cutting-edge AI technology, but your team doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand how it works, when it might fail, or what legal obligations come with its use. Sound familiar? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone—and you&amp;rsquo;re potentially in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.lexia.it/en/2025/05/30/ai-literacy-and-faqs/"&gt;European AI Act&lt;/a&gt;, which mandates AI literacy training as of February 2, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-knowledge-first-imperative"&gt;The Knowledge-First Imperative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle is simple yet revolutionary: &lt;strong&gt;knowledge is power, and it&amp;rsquo;s crucial for successful AI integration to have educated personnel first, not after integration&lt;/strong&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just good practice—it&amp;rsquo;s now a legal requirement under EU regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>SMS Security Crisis: Hackers Selling SS7 Vulnerability for $5,000, Exposing Millions to Surveillance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 05:55:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Perfect Storm for Information Security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in the cybersecurity landscape have created what I can only describe as a perfect storm for organizations maintaining ISO 27001 certification. A &lt;a href="https://cybersecuritynews.com/hackers-selling-ss7-0-day-vulnerability/"&gt;critical vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_System_No._7"&gt;Signaling System 7 (SS7)&lt;/a&gt; protocol – the backbone of global telecommunications – is now being marketed on underground forums for a mere $5,000, dramatically lowering the barrier to entry for sophisticated telecom-based attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-matters-for-iso-27001-certified-organizations"&gt;Why This Matters for ISO 27001 Certified Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those maintaining ISO 27001 certification, this development has significant implications across multiple control domains:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Model Context Protocol: A Security Threat Masquerading as Innovation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 19:40:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The tech world is abuzz with discussions about the Model Context Protocol (MCP), but security experts are raising red flags that should concern every organization considering its implementation. Far from being the revolutionary protocol its proponents claim, MCP may represent a significant security vulnerability that could compromise sensitive data and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP purports to facilitate communication between language models and external tools, creating a standardized way for AI systems to access data sources and execute functions. However, as detailed in a recent analysis, this so-called &amp;ldquo;protocol&amp;rdquo; is more accurately described as a scheme that lacks fundamental security safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU's ProtectEU Plan Sparks Privacy Concerns: The Hidden Cost of Backdoored Encryption</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 08:52:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a move that has sent shockwaves through the cybersecurity community, &lt;a href="https://home-affairs.ec.europa.eu/news/commission-presents-protecteu-internal-security-strategy-2025-04-01_en"&gt;the European Union&amp;rsquo;s ProtectEU&lt;/a&gt; plan has revealed ambitious proposals to implement encryption backdoors by 2026. This development raises critical questions about the future of digital privacy and security in the EU&amp;rsquo;s increasingly regulated cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan, which extends far beyond encryption concerns, encompasses several significant initiatives. At its core, the proposal aims to enhance law enforcement capabilities, particularly in fighting serious crimes and child sexual abuse. However, the controversial encryption backdoor requirement has become a focal point of debate.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Thinking About Deploying AI Agents? Read This First.</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 08:42:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;So, your team is buzzing about the latest AI agents – those clever systems that can automate complex tasks, maybe even act as personal assistants? They sound fantastic, promising leaps in productivity. But before you dive headfirst into deployment, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about a critical risk NIST is highlighting: &lt;strong&gt;agent hijacking&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Agent Hijacking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine an attacker slipping malicious instructions into the data your shiny new AI agent uses. Suddenly, instead of helping, it&amp;rsquo;s performing harmful actions you never intended. That&amp;rsquo;s agent hijacking, a sneaky form of indirect prompt injection, and it&amp;rsquo;s a real threat.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Modernizing Penetration Testing Reports: The Case for Standardization</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 08:18:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In an era where cyber threats evolve at lightning speed, it&amp;rsquo;s puzzling that many organizations still handle penetration testing reports like they did two decades ago. The current process is a familiar dance: consultants meticulously document their findings in Word documents, convert them to PDFs, email them to clients, who then manually copy and paste the data into their issue tracking systems. This inefficient workflow isn&amp;rsquo;t just outdated—it&amp;rsquo;s actively hindering our industry&amp;rsquo;s ability to respond to security threats effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>