<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Cryptography on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/cryptography/</link><description>Recent content in Cryptography on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/cryptography/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EDPB Guidelines Expose Blockchain's GDPR Nightmare: Is BitTorrent the Unexpected Solution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 08:32:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building on &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/blockchain.asp"&gt;blockchain technology&lt;/a&gt; without considering the privacy compliance minefield you&amp;rsquo;re walking into? The &lt;a href="https://edpb.europa.eu/"&gt;European Data Protection Board&amp;rsquo;s (EDPB)&lt;/a&gt; latest guidelines reveal a fundamental incompatibility between blockchain&amp;rsquo;s core features and &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; requirements that could derail your digital transformation plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-immutability-problem"&gt;The Immutability Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength - its &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/immutable-ledger"&gt;immutable ledger&lt;/a&gt; - has become its GDPR Achilles&amp;rsquo; heel. &lt;a href="https://www.williamfry.com/knowledge/edpb-guidelines-raise-questions-on-how-gdpr-interacts-with-blockchain/"&gt;According to new EDPB guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, the technology&amp;rsquo;s inability to modify or delete records directly conflicts with data subjects&amp;rsquo; rights to erasure and rectification under &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-17-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR Articles 17&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-16-gdpr/"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Switzerland's Fintech Revolution: Are You Missing Europe's Most Crypto-Friendly Business Hub?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:46:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still navigating the complex maze of European &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fintech.asp"&gt;fintech&lt;/a&gt; regulations while your competitors establish operations in Switzerland? While the European Union continues to wrestle with comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/cryptocurrency.asp"&gt;crypto&lt;/a&gt; frameworks, Switzerland has quietly positioned itself as the continent&amp;rsquo;s most fintech-friendly jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to recognize that the European fintech landscape is rapidly evolving, with multiple jurisdictions now competing to attract innovation. Countries like the &lt;a href="https://www.fca.org.uk/firms/innovation"&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.bafin.de/EN/Aufsicht/FinTech/fintech_node_en.html"&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt; have implemented robust &lt;a href="https://www.planetcompliance.com/compliance-software/innovation-hubs-v-regulatory-sandboxes-and-the-future-of-innovation-facilitators/"&gt;regulatory sandboxes&lt;/a&gt; and innovation hubs that provide fintech companies with controlled environments to test new products without full regulatory compliance burdens.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Embeddings as Secure as You Think?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:49:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your organization&amp;rsquo;s AI embeddings are protecting sensitive information? A groundbreaking new research paper reveals a troubling reality: what you thought was secure data representation might be an open book to determined attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are AI embeddings?&lt;/strong&gt; For readers new to this concept, &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ai/what-are-embeddings/"&gt;embeddings are numerical representations&lt;/a&gt; that convert complex data like text, images, or audio into mathematical vectors that AI systems can process. Think of them as a way to translate human-readable information into a language that machines understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secure Minions: The Game-Changer That Could Revolutionize Your AI Privacy Strategy</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you unknowingly exposing your sensitive data every time you use cloud-based AI?&lt;/strong&gt; A groundbreaking collaboration between &lt;a href="https://ollama.com/blog/secureminions"&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://hazyresearch.stanford.edu/blog/2025-05-12-security"&gt;Stanford&amp;rsquo;s Hazy Research&lt;/a&gt; might have just solved one of AI&amp;rsquo;s most pressing privacy dilemmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-privacy-problem-you-didnt-know-you-had"&gt;The Privacy Problem You Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know You Had&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time your organization sends data to cloud-based frontier models like GPT-4 or Claude, you&amp;rsquo;re essentially handing over your sensitive information to third parties. For businesses handling confidential data, this creates a compliance nightmare and potential security breach waiting to happen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>SMS Security Crisis: Hackers Selling SS7 Vulnerability for $5,000, Exposing Millions to Surveillance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 05:55:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Perfect Storm for Information Security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in the cybersecurity landscape have created what I can only describe as a perfect storm for organizations maintaining ISO 27001 certification. A &lt;a href="https://cybersecuritynews.com/hackers-selling-ss7-0-day-vulnerability/"&gt;critical vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_System_No._7"&gt;Signaling System 7 (SS7)&lt;/a&gt; protocol – the backbone of global telecommunications – is now being marketed on underground forums for a mere $5,000, dramatically lowering the barrier to entry for sophisticated telecom-based attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-matters-for-iso-27001-certified-organizations"&gt;Why This Matters for ISO 27001 Certified Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those maintaining ISO 27001 certification, this development has significant implications across multiple control domains:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU's ProtectEU Plan Sparks Privacy Concerns: The Hidden Cost of Backdoored Encryption</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 08:52:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a move that has sent shockwaves through the cybersecurity community, &lt;a href="https://home-affairs.ec.europa.eu/news/commission-presents-protecteu-internal-security-strategy-2025-04-01_en"&gt;the European Union&amp;rsquo;s ProtectEU&lt;/a&gt; plan has revealed ambitious proposals to implement encryption backdoors by 2026. This development raises critical questions about the future of digital privacy and security in the EU&amp;rsquo;s increasingly regulated cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan, which extends far beyond encryption concerns, encompasses several significant initiatives. At its core, the proposal aims to enhance law enforcement capabilities, particularly in fighting serious crimes and child sexual abuse. However, the controversial encryption backdoor requirement has become a focal point of debate.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>