<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Ml on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/ml/</link><description>Recent content in Ml on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/ml/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is Your Enterprise Database Strategy Ready for the Foundation Model Revolution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still moving data to AI algorithms instead of bringing AI to your data? &lt;a href="https://kumo.ai/company/news/kumo-relational-foundation-model/"&gt;Kumo AI&amp;rsquo;s KumoRFM&lt;/a&gt; shows a fundamental shift that could reshape how enterprises handle their most valuable asset: structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-game-changing-approach"&gt;The Game-Changing Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KumoRFM represents the first Relational Foundation Model (RFM) designed specifically for structured and relational data. Unlike traditional AI models that require extensive task-specific training and costly data migration, KumoRFM leverages &lt;strong&gt;in-context learning&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver accurate predictions across diverse databases without retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Algorithmic Transparency Matters</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 12:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Has your team been excitedly pitching you the latest AI automation system that promises to revolutionize customer assessments, credit decisions, or resource allocation? Before you sign off on that purchase order, there&amp;rsquo;s something you should know: the EU courts just made it crystal clear that algorithmic transparency isn&amp;rsquo;t optional - it&amp;rsquo;s mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-eu-court-just-raised-the-stakes"&gt;The EU Court Just Raised the Stakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a landmark judgment (&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=295841&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=15436379"&gt;Case C‑203/22&lt;/a&gt;) delivered on February 27, 2025, the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has provided crucial clarity on what companies must disclose when they use automated decision-making systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Adventures in Setting Up NVIDIA's GH200 Grace Hopper: A Tale of Two Systems</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 18:01:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I had the exciting opportunity to set up one of NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s most powerful AI computing platforms - the Grace Hopper Superchip (GH200). What makes this setup particularly interesting is that it&amp;rsquo;s actually two systems in one: the main Grace Hopper CPU-GPU system and the BlueField-3 DPU (Data Processing Unit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-the-hardware"&gt;Understanding the Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GH200 combines NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s Grace CPU with a Hopper GPU architecture, creating a powerhouse for AI and high-performance computing workloads. The BlueField-3 DPU is essentially a network card on steroids - it&amp;rsquo;s a specialized processor that handles networking, storage, and security tasks, freeing up the main system for computational work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting Guide: Accessing NotebookLM Plus with Google Workspace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 07:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As organizations increasingly adopt AI-powered tools, Google&amp;rsquo;s NotebookLM Plus has emerged as a valuable resource for businesses. However, many users encounter access issues due to specific licensing and configuration requirements. After an in-depth troubleshooting session with a Google representative, we&amp;rsquo;ve compiled a comprehensive guide to help you navigate these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-requirements-for-notebooklm-plus-access"&gt;Key Requirements for NotebookLM Plus Access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="licensing-prerequisites"&gt;Licensing Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of NotebookLM Plus access lies in proper licensing. Here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>INTELLECT-1: A Groundbreaking Open-Source AI Model</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 08:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting news in the AI community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/lmstudio-community/INTELLECT-1-Instruct-GGUF"&gt;INTELLECT-1&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Prime Intellect with Arcee AI, represents a remarkable achievement in collaborative innovation. This fully open-source model stands out by transparently sharing its entire development process, from dataset to algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively created through distributed computing across 30 contributors from 5 countries, INTELLECT-1 isn&amp;rsquo;t just another fine-tuned model—it&amp;rsquo;s a fresh, ground-up approach that promises unique capabilities. Check out this pioneering project and support its innovative spirit!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>