<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Regualtion on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/regualtion/</link><description>Recent content in Regualtion on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:30:55 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/regualtion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>EU Digital Omnibus Drops: Is Your Compliance Strategy About to Become Obsolete?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/25/eu-digital-omnibus-drops-is-your-compliance-strategy-about-to-become-obsolete/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:30:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/25/eu-digital-omnibus-drops-is-your-compliance-strategy-about-to-become-obsolete/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still building your compliance framework around the current GDPR, AI Act, and Data Act requirements? The European Commission just published the most sweeping reform of EU digital laws since 2018 - and everything you thought you knew about data protection compliance might be about to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-regulatory-earthquake-you-cant-ignore"&gt;The Regulatory Earthquake You Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 November 2025, the European Commission released two proposed regulations that will fundamentally reshape how businesses handle data, AI, and cybersecurity in Europe. The Digital Omnibus (2025/0360) and Digital Omnibus on AI (2025/0359) aren&amp;rsquo;t minor tweaks - they&amp;rsquo;re a complete rethinking of the EU&amp;rsquo;s approach to digital regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Italy Breaks New Ground: Europe's First National AI Law Is Here – Is Your Business Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/07/italy-breaks-new-ground-europes-first-national-ai-law-is-here-is-your-business-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 12:40:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/07/italy-breaks-new-ground-europes-first-national-ai-law-is-here-is-your-business-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you prepared for the regulatory shift that could redefine how your business operates with AI?&lt;/strong&gt; Italy has just made history by becoming the first European Union member state to pass comprehensive national artificial intelligence legislation, and the implications extend far beyond Italian borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-landmark-decision-that-changes-everything"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Landmark Decision That Changes Everything&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On September 17, 2025, the Italian Parliament approved &lt;a href="https://www.mwe.com/insights/italy-becomes-the-first-in-europe-to-set-national-ai-rules/"&gt;Law No. 132 of 23 September 2025&lt;/a&gt;, officially taking effect on October 10, 2025. This groundbreaking legislation doesn&amp;rsquo;t just complement the &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/high-level-summary/"&gt;EU AI Act&lt;/a&gt; – the European Union&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive framework that &lt;a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/topics/en/article/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence"&gt;classifies AI systems by risk levels&lt;/a&gt; – it fills critical gaps and establishes precedents that other European nations are likely to follow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Agents Legally Compliant? The Regulatory Reality Check Every Business Must Face</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:46:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you deploying &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; without understanding the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re navigating? While competitors rush to automate processes with intelligent agents, smart organizations are discovering that regulatory compliance - not just functionality - determines long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-multi-framework-challenge-thats-catching-everyone-off-guard"&gt;The Multi-Framework Challenge That&amp;rsquo;s Catching Everyone Off Guard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salesforce.com/resources/articles/ai-agent/"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t operate in a regulatory vacuum. Unlike traditional software, these autonomous systems must simultaneously comply with multiple overlapping frameworks that create unprecedented complexity for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Your AI Startup Needs Aviation-Grade Regulation: Lessons from 100 Years of Flight Safety</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 11:57:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building your AI startup without considering the regulatory framework that could make or break your venture? While entrepreneurs rush to deploy the latest artificial intelligence solutions, the smartest founders are looking to an unexpected mentor: the aviation industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-striking-parallels-you-cant-ignore"&gt;The Striking Parallels You Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as aviation transformed from experimental flights to a trillion-dollar industry through rigorous safety standards, AI is following a remarkably similar trajectory. Both industries share three critical characteristics that suggest valuable regulatory lessons, though important differences must be acknowledged:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>