<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Legal on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/</link><description>Recent content in Legal on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 13:04:38 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Disclaimer</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/digitaliziran-si-disclaimer/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 13:04:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/digitaliziran-si-disclaimer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The information provided on digitaliziran.si (the &amp;ldquo;Site&amp;rdquo;) is for general informational purposes only. While We strive to keep the information up to date and accurate, We make no representations or warranties of any kind, express or implied, about the completeness, accuracy, reliability, suitability, or availability of the information, products, services, or related graphics contained on the Site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="professional-advice"&gt;Professional Advice&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Any reliance you place on information from this Site is strictly at your own risk. The content on this Site should not be considered as a substitute for professional advice. You should consult with appropriate professionals for specific advice tailored to your situation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Terms and Conditions</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/terms-and-conditions/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 13:02:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/terms-and-conditions/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="1-introduction"&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These Terms and conditions apply to this website and to the transactions related to our products and services. You may be bound by additional contracts related to your relationship with us or any products or services that you receive from us. If any provisions of the additional contracts conflict with any provisions of these Terms, the provisions of these additional contracts will control and prevail.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2-binding"&gt;2. Binding&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By registering with, accessing, or otherwise using this website, you hereby agree to be bound by these Terms and conditions set forth below. The mere use of this website implies the knowledge and acceptance of these Terms and conditions. In some particular cases, we can also ask you to explicitly agree.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Code of Ethics &amp; Professional Conduct</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/code-of-ethics-professional-conduct/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 12:51:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/code-of-ethics-professional-conduct/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="our-commitment"&gt;Our Commitment&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are committed to maintaining the highest standards of professional conduct and ethical behavior in all our AI and digital transformation endeavors. This code outlines our core principles and commitments to our clients, partners, and the broader community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="professional-standards"&gt;Professional Standards&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We maintain current knowledge of AI technologies, methodologies, and industry best practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We hold relevant certifications and continuously pursue professional development&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We adhere to ISO42001 standards and other applicable international frameworks&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We collaborate only with qualified professionals who share our ethical standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="client-relations"&gt;Client Relations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We provide honest and realistic assessments of AI implementation possibilities&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We maintain strict confidentiality of client information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We recommend solutions based on client needs, not commercial interests&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We clearly communicate both opportunities and limitations of proposed solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="data-ethics"&gt;Data Ethics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We prioritize data privacy and security in all implementations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We advocate for responsible AI development and deployment&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We ensure transparency in data collection and processing methods&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We implement appropriate safeguards for sensitive information&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="quality-assurance"&gt;Quality Assurance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We deliver solutions that meet or exceed industry standards&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We maintain detailed documentation of our processes&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We regularly review and update our methodologies&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We take responsibility for the quality of our work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="conflict-of-interest"&gt;Conflict of Interest&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We disclose any potential conflicts of interest&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We maintain independence in our assessments and recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We do not accept assignments that could compromise our objectivity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We prioritize client interests while maintaining professional integrity&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="environmental-responsibility"&gt;Environmental Responsibility&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We consider environmental impact in our solutions&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We promote sustainable AI implementations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We optimize resource usage in our recommendations&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="continuous-improvement"&gt;Continuous Improvement&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We regularly review and update our practices&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We welcome feedback from clients and partners&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We adapt our methods based on industry developments&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;We share knowledge to advance the field while respecting confidentiality&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contact"&gt;Contact&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For any questions regarding our ethical standards or professional conduct, please contact us through our official channels listed on our website.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Contact Information</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/contact-information/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 12:46:31 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/contact-information/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="business-details"&gt;Business Details&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Company Name:&lt;/strong&gt; Grigory Evseev s.p.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Registration Number:&lt;/strong&gt; 8558639000&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;VAT ID:&lt;/strong&gt; SI47868538&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="location"&gt;Location&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Address:&lt;/strong&gt; Železniška ulica 5, 4248 Lesce, Slovenia, EU&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="professional-certifications"&gt;Professional Certifications&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ISO/IEC 27001 Information Security Management Systems Lead Auditor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;AIRBUS Safety Management System (SMS) Auditor&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;ISO/IEC 42001 AI Management Systems (Pre-certification)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h2 id="contact-methods"&gt;Contact Methods&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Email:&lt;/strong&gt; info at digitaliziran.si&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We specialize in AI implementation, auditing, and consulting services, with extensive experience in aviation, banking, and insurance sectors. Our expertise includes both offline and cloud-based AI solutions, with a particular focus on handling sensitive data securely.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cookie Policy</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/cookie-policy-eu/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 18:29:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/cookie-policy-eu/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This Cookie Policy applies to citizens and legal permanent residents of the European Economic Area and Switzerland.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="1-introduction"&gt;1. Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our website, &lt;a href="https://digitaliziran.si"&gt;https://digitaliziran.si&lt;/a&gt; (hereinafter: &amp;ldquo;the website&amp;rdquo;) uses cookies and other related technologies (for convenience all technologies are referred to as &amp;ldquo;cookies&amp;rdquo;). Cookies are also placed by third parties we have engaged. In the document below we inform you about the use of cookies on our website.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="2-what-are-cookies"&gt;2. What are cookies?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A cookie is a small simple file that is sent along with pages of this website and stored by your browser on the hard drive of your computer or another device. The information stored therein may be returned to our servers or to the servers of the relevant third parties during a subsequent visit.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Privacy Policy</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/privacy-policy/</link><pubDate>Sun, 12 Mar 2023 16:06:32 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/pages/legal/privacy-policy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Effective Date: March 12, 2023&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="i-data-processing-in-general"&gt;I. Data Processing in General&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="scope-of-the-processing-of-personal-data"&gt;Scope of the Processing of Personal Data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The processing of personal data is limited to data that is required to operate a functional website and for the provision of content and services. The processing of personal data of our users is based on the purposes agreed or on a legal basis (GDPR). We only collect personal data that is necessary to implement and process our tasks and services or if you provide data voluntarily.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>