<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Eli5 on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/eli5/</link><description>Recent content in Eli5 on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 12:35:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/eli5/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why Algorithmic Transparency Matters</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 12:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Has your team been excitedly pitching you the latest AI automation system that promises to revolutionize customer assessments, credit decisions, or resource allocation? Before you sign off on that purchase order, there&amp;rsquo;s something you should know: the EU courts just made it crystal clear that algorithmic transparency isn&amp;rsquo;t optional - it&amp;rsquo;s mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-eu-court-just-raised-the-stakes"&gt;The EU Court Just Raised the Stakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a landmark judgment (&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=295841&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=15436379"&gt;Case C‑203/22&lt;/a&gt;) delivered on February 27, 2025, the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has provided crucial clarity on what companies must disclose when they use automated decision-making systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reminder #1</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 19:59:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distributed system&lt;/em&gt; is a characteristic of the deployment model, not of the code organization model.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Yerkes-Dodson's Law: Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you find yourself either stressing out or being lazy all the time? Well, according to Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law, both of these behaviors can have negative consequences on your productivity and overall well-being. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the science behind this law and explain why it&amp;rsquo;s important to find a balance between stress and laziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad-yerkes-dodsons-law-explained"&gt;Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad: Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law Explained&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law is a psychological principle that explains the relationship between stress and performance. Essentially, the law states that there is an optimal level of stress that leads to peak performance, but too much or too little stress can actually hinder productivity. This means that both too much stress and too much relaxation can be detrimental to your success.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zakaj stres ni vedno slaba stvar? Yerkes-Dodsonov zakon: ELI5</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stres pogosto velja za sovražnika produktivnosti in sreče. Kaj pa, če vam povemo, da stres ni vedno slaba stvar? V skladu z Yerkes-Dodsonovim zakonom je lahko malo stresa dejansko koristno. Preden se prestrašite zaradi prihajajočega roka ali predstavitve, preberite, zakaj je stres morda vendarle vaš prijatelj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ste-pod-stresom-ne-prestrašite-se-še"&gt;Ste pod stresom? Ne prestrašite se&amp;hellip; še!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vsi smo se že kdaj srečali s prepotenimi dlanmi, pospešenim bitjem srca in strahovitim občutkom strahu, ki se pojavijo ob stresu. Toda preden posežete po Xanaxu, upoštevajte naslednje: malo stresa lahko dejansko izboljša vašo učinkovitost. Res je, stres vas lahko motivira, saj vam pomaga, da se osredotočite in ostanete budni. Težava nastane šele, ko stres postane preobsežen in kroničen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>