<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>DORA on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/dora/</link><description>Recent content in DORA on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/dora/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Your AI Procurement Strategy Could Be Your Biggest Compliance Risk: What Financial Services Must Know</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to procure AI solutions for your financial services firm without considering the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re entering? While competitors scramble to deploy the latest AI tools, smart institutions are discovering that &lt;strong&gt;procurement strategy - not just implementation - determines compliance success&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-procurement-blind-spot-thats-costing-millions"&gt;The Procurement Blind Spot That&amp;rsquo;s Costing Millions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most financial institutions approach AI procurement like any other technology purchase. This is a critical mistake. Unlike traditional software, AI systems in financial services must navigate an intricate web of regulations including the &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; - the EU&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive data privacy law that governs how personal information must be handled - &lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt; - a new EU regulation requiring financial institutions to strengthen their digital resilience against cyber threats - and emerging &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/"&gt;AI-specific legislation&lt;/a&gt; like the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>DORA First: Why Financial Institutions Must Prioritize AI Readiness Before 2027</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/dora-first-why-financial-institutions-must-prioritize-ai-readiness-before-2027/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:50:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/dora-first-why-financial-institutions-must-prioritize-ai-readiness-before-2027/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the regulatory storm heading toward financial services? While your competitors scramble to understand the &lt;a href="https://www.artificial-intelligence-act.com/"&gt;EU AI Act&lt;/a&gt;, smart institutions are taking a &amp;ldquo;DORA first&amp;rdquo; approach - and it might be the difference between thriving and merely surviving the 2027 compliance deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfect-storm-when-dora-meets-ai-act"&gt;The Perfect Storm: When DORA Meets AI Act&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.mofo.com/resources/insights/250218-european-digital-compliance-key-digital-regulation-compliance"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt;, which became applicable on &lt;strong&gt;January 17, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, has already transformed how financial institutions manage &lt;a href="https://www.leanix.net/en/wiki/trm/ict-risk-management-under-dora"&gt;ICT risk&lt;/a&gt; (Information and Communication Technology risks that could compromise network and information systems). Now, with the &lt;a href="https://www.skadden.com/insights/publications/2024/10/eu-standardization-supporting-the-artificial-intelligence-act"&gt;EU AI Act&amp;rsquo;s full enforcement approaching August 2, 2027&lt;/a&gt;, institutions face an unprecedented convergence of regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>