<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>General on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/general/</link><description>Recent content in General on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/general/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is Your Organization Ready for the AI Officer Revolution? The Critical Role Reshaping Corporate Governance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the executive role that&amp;rsquo;s quietly becoming one of the most discussed positions in modern corporate governance? While companies scramble to implement &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/artificial-intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; solutions, a new breed of executive is emerging to navigate the complex intersection of technology, ethics, and regulatory compliance: the AI Officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-rise-of-the-ai-officer-more-than-just-another-c-suite-title"&gt;The Rise of the AI Officer: More Than Just Another C-Suite Title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI Officer role represents a significant shift in how organizations approach artificial intelligence governance. Unlike traditional technology roles, &lt;a href="https://www.vantedgesearch.com/resources/blogs-the-caio-emergence-why-the-chief-ai-officer-is-todays-critical-c-suite-role/"&gt;AI Officers concentrate accountability for value creation and risk control&lt;/a&gt; that was previously scattered across IT, data, and business units.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Silent Standard: Why ISO/IEC 42005 Could Be Your Agentic AI Safety Net</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:32:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the autonomous AI revolution that&amp;rsquo;s already knocking at your door? While &lt;a href="https://www.riskinsight-wavestone.com/2025/07/ia-agentic-typologie-des-risques-et-principales-mesures-de-securite/"&gt;Gartner identifies agentic AI as a strategic trend for 2025&lt;/a&gt;, there&amp;rsquo;s a critical piece of the puzzle that most professionals are overlooking: &lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/42005"&gt;ISO/IEC 42005:2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-agentic-ai-reality-check"&gt;The Agentic AI Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/insights/ai-agents-2025-expectations-vs-reality"&gt;Agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t just respond to prompts - they &lt;strong&gt;plan, execute, and act autonomously&lt;/strong&gt; based on their environment. Think of them as digital employees who can book meetings, analyze data, and make decisions without constant supervision. But here&amp;rsquo;s the uncomfortable truth: this autonomy comes with unprecedented risks.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Amazon's AI Assistant Nearly Wiped Developer Systems for 5 Days – Are Your Access Controls Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 19:14:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Picture this scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re working late, relying on your trusted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI-assisted_programming"&gt;AI coding assistant&lt;/a&gt; to help debug a critical application. Unknown to you, that same assistant has been compromised and is quietly preparing to execute commands that could wipe your entire development environment – both local files and cloud infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a hypothetical nightmare. It actually happened to &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/q/developer/"&gt;Amazon Q Developer Extension&lt;/a&gt; users for five consecutive days, and the implications should make every &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_information_security_officer"&gt;Chief Information Security Officer (CISO)&lt;/a&gt; reassess their AI integration strategies immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Procurement Strategy Could Be Your Biggest Compliance Risk: What Financial Services Must Know</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to procure AI solutions for your financial services firm without considering the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re entering? While competitors scramble to deploy the latest AI tools, smart institutions are discovering that &lt;strong&gt;procurement strategy - not just implementation - determines compliance success&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-procurement-blind-spot-thats-costing-millions"&gt;The Procurement Blind Spot That&amp;rsquo;s Costing Millions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most financial institutions approach AI procurement like any other technology purchase. This is a critical mistake. Unlike traditional software, AI systems in financial services must navigate an intricate web of regulations including the &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; - the EU&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive data privacy law that governs how personal information must be handled - &lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt; - a new EU regulation requiring financial institutions to strengthen their digital resilience against cyber threats - and emerging &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/"&gt;AI-specific legislation&lt;/a&gt; like the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>MCP's Hidden Security Crisis: Why Your AI Automation Strategy Needs an Urgent Reality Check</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 16:33:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to implement &lt;a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/model-context-protocol"&gt;Model Context Protocol (MCP)&lt;/a&gt; for your AI automation workflows? Before you do, consider this sobering reality: &lt;a href="https://blog.sshh.io/p/everything-wrong-with-mcp"&gt;MCP may be creating more security vulnerabilities than it solves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Promise vs. The Reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-06-18"&gt;MCP&lt;/a&gt; promises seamless integration between &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/large-language-models"&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/a&gt; and third-party tools, positioning itself as the standard for AI-driven automation. Companies are adopting it to streamline workflows, reduce manual processes, and give &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; unprecedented control over business operations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EDPB Guidelines Expose Blockchain's GDPR Nightmare: Is BitTorrent the Unexpected Solution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 08:32:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building on &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/blockchain.asp"&gt;blockchain technology&lt;/a&gt; without considering the privacy compliance minefield you&amp;rsquo;re walking into? The &lt;a href="https://edpb.europa.eu/"&gt;European Data Protection Board&amp;rsquo;s (EDPB)&lt;/a&gt; latest guidelines reveal a fundamental incompatibility between blockchain&amp;rsquo;s core features and &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; requirements that could derail your digital transformation plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-immutability-problem"&gt;The Immutability Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength - its &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/immutable-ledger"&gt;immutable ledger&lt;/a&gt; - has become its GDPR Achilles&amp;rsquo; heel. &lt;a href="https://www.williamfry.com/knowledge/edpb-guidelines-raise-questions-on-how-gdpr-interacts-with-blockchain/"&gt;According to new EDPB guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, the technology&amp;rsquo;s inability to modify or delete records directly conflicts with data subjects&amp;rsquo; rights to erasure and rectification under &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-17-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR Articles 17&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-16-gdpr/"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>