<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Research on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/research/</link><description>Recent content in Research on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:16:37 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/research/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is Your Business Ready for Europe's AI Language Revolution? Microsoft's Bold Move Could Leave You Behind</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:16:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you considered whether your AI tools truly understand your customers&amp;rsquo; native languages? If you&amp;rsquo;re operating in Europe&amp;rsquo;s diverse linguistic landscape, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s latest announcement should make you pause and reassess your digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-wake-up-call-europe-needed"&gt;The Wake-Up Call Europe Needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft recently launched two initiatives that could reshape how AI serves Europe&amp;rsquo;s 200+ languages, though the impact may be more incremental than revolutionary. The tech giant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/on-the-issues/2025/07/20/eudigitalunlock/"&gt;European Digital Unlock program&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t just another corporate initiative - it&amp;rsquo;s a direct response to a critical gap that&amp;rsquo;s been undermining European businesses for years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EDPB Guidelines Expose Blockchain's GDPR Nightmare: Is BitTorrent the Unexpected Solution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 08:32:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building on &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/blockchain.asp"&gt;blockchain technology&lt;/a&gt; without considering the privacy compliance minefield you&amp;rsquo;re walking into? The &lt;a href="https://edpb.europa.eu/"&gt;European Data Protection Board&amp;rsquo;s (EDPB)&lt;/a&gt; latest guidelines reveal a fundamental incompatibility between blockchain&amp;rsquo;s core features and &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; requirements that could derail your digital transformation plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-immutability-problem"&gt;The Immutability Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength - its &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/immutable-ledger"&gt;immutable ledger&lt;/a&gt; - has become its GDPR Achilles&amp;rsquo; heel. &lt;a href="https://www.williamfry.com/knowledge/edpb-guidelines-raise-questions-on-how-gdpr-interacts-with-blockchain/"&gt;According to new EDPB guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, the technology&amp;rsquo;s inability to modify or delete records directly conflicts with data subjects&amp;rsquo; rights to erasure and rectification under &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-17-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR Articles 17&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-16-gdpr/"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your IT Audits Ready for the AI Revolution? Five Game-Changing Applications You Can't Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still conducting IT audits the traditional way while your competitors leverage artificial intelligence to uncover risks you might miss? A recent &lt;a href="https://www.isaca.org/resources/news-and-trends/isaca-now-blog/2025/five-ways-that-it-auditors-can-put-ai-to-good-use"&gt;ISACA analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals five transformative applications of AI in IT auditing that could revolutionize how you approach risk assessment and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-audit-advantage-beyond-human-limitations"&gt;The AI Audit Advantage: Beyond Human Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional auditing methods, while thorough, face inherent constraints: time limitations, human error, and the sheer volume of data in modern organizations. AI transforms these challenges into opportunities through &lt;strong&gt;risk analysis automation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;intelligent evidence collection&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;continuous controls testing&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;real-time assurance monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;comprehensive process automation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Enterprise Database Strategy Ready for the Foundation Model Revolution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still moving data to AI algorithms instead of bringing AI to your data? &lt;a href="https://kumo.ai/company/news/kumo-relational-foundation-model/"&gt;Kumo AI&amp;rsquo;s KumoRFM&lt;/a&gt; shows a fundamental shift that could reshape how enterprises handle their most valuable asset: structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-game-changing-approach"&gt;The Game-Changing Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KumoRFM represents the first Relational Foundation Model (RFM) designed specifically for structured and relational data. Unlike traditional AI models that require extensive task-specific training and costly data migration, KumoRFM leverages &lt;strong&gt;in-context learning&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver accurate predictions across diverse databases without retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Automation Paradox - When Machines Make Humans More Crucial</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/28/the-automation-paradox-when-machines-make-humans-more-crucial/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 15:23:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/28/the-automation-paradox-when-machines-make-humans-more-crucial/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For decades, the promise of automation has been clear: machines taking over tedious, error-prone tasks, freeing up humans for more strategic and creative endeavors. Yet, as early as 1983, Lisanne Bainbridge highlighted a fascinating paradox in her seminal work, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200717054958if_/https://www.ise.ncsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Bainbridge_1983_Automatica.pdf"&gt;Ironies of Automation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;. She observed that the more advanced an automated system becomes, the more critical the role of the human operator often becomes. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the straightforward efficiency gain one might expect; instead, it introduces a new set of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Adventures in Setting Up NVIDIA's GH200 Grace Hopper: A Tale of Two Systems</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 18:01:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I had the exciting opportunity to set up one of NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s most powerful AI computing platforms - the Grace Hopper Superchip (GH200). What makes this setup particularly interesting is that it&amp;rsquo;s actually two systems in one: the main Grace Hopper CPU-GPU system and the BlueField-3 DPU (Data Processing Unit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-the-hardware"&gt;Understanding the Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GH200 combines NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s Grace CPU with a Hopper GPU architecture, creating a powerhouse for AI and high-performance computing workloads. The BlueField-3 DPU is essentially a network card on steroids - it&amp;rsquo;s a specialized processor that handles networking, storage, and security tasks, freeing up the main system for computational work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting Guide: Accessing NotebookLM Plus with Google Workspace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 07:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As organizations increasingly adopt AI-powered tools, Google&amp;rsquo;s NotebookLM Plus has emerged as a valuable resource for businesses. However, many users encounter access issues due to specific licensing and configuration requirements. After an in-depth troubleshooting session with a Google representative, we&amp;rsquo;ve compiled a comprehensive guide to help you navigate these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-requirements-for-notebooklm-plus-access"&gt;Key Requirements for NotebookLM Plus Access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="licensing-prerequisites"&gt;Licensing Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of NotebookLM Plus access lies in proper licensing. Here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>