<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Blog on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/posts/</link><description>Recent content in Blog on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Emperor Has No ROI</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2026/01/19/emperor-has-no-roi/</link><pubDate>Mon, 19 Jan 2026 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2026/01/19/emperor-has-no-roi/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Or: How to Cut Headcount and Multiply Costs&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-pitch-vs-the-spreadsheet"&gt;The Pitch vs. The Spreadsheet&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;rsquo;ve seen the headlines. You&amp;rsquo;ve attended the boardroom presentations. Some consultant with expensive slides told you AI will &amp;ldquo;transform your workforce&amp;rdquo; and you nodded along while mentally calculating severance packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before you start drafting those redundancy letters, let&amp;rsquo;s talk numbers. Not the shiny projected ones. The real ones.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h2 id="95-of-ai-projects-return-exactly-nothing"&gt;95% of AI Projects Return Exactly Nothing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://campustechnology.com/articles/2025/08/26/mit-report-most-organizations-see-no-business-return-on-gen-ai-investments.aspx"&gt;MIT&amp;rsquo;s 2025 report &amp;ldquo;The GenAI Divide&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; dropped a truth bomb: despite &lt;strong&gt;$30-40 billion&lt;/strong&gt; in enterprise AI investment, &lt;a href="https://www.entrepreneur.com/business-news/most-companies-saw-zero-return-on-ai-investments-study/496144"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;95% of organizations report zero measurable return&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/a&gt; on their AI pilots.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>2026+: What to Do When Everyone Can Do Everything</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/12/30/2026-what-to-do-when-everyone-can-do-everything/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Dec 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/12/30/2026-what-to-do-when-everyone-can-do-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;2025 was the year of simplification. Complex workflows collapsed into a few buttons. The distance between &amp;ldquo;I want this&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;done&amp;rdquo; is approaching zero. Soon we&amp;rsquo;ll be generating things through neural interfaces paired with AI agents. (Screenshot this.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now everyone can make anything - and everyone does. Content factories pump out AI-generated slop at industrial scale. Algorithms lock us into bubbles of perfectly curated comfort: soft, familiar, frictionless. Reels, shorts, endless scroll. Attention has become reflexive. In this ocean of noise, good ideas drown as quickly as bad ones.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU Court Ruling Forces Marketplaces to Verify User Data Before Publishing: Is Your Platform Compliant?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/12/02/eu-court-ruling-forces-marketplaces-to-verify-user-data-before-publishing-is-your-platform-compliant/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Dec 2025 17:11:12 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/12/02/eu-court-ruling-forces-marketplaces-to-verify-user-data-before-publishing-is-your-platform-compliant/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Does your online marketplace publish user-generated listings without verifying the personal data they contain? A &lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf;jsessionid=E541D6943FA2B3D1E87A0FCA78DCF7D7?text=&amp;amp;docid=306764&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=req&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=15422674"&gt;landmark ruling from the Court of Justice of the European Union&lt;/a&gt; in &lt;em&gt;Russmedia Digital&lt;/em&gt; (C-492/23) just fundamentally changed how platforms must handle &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/issues/personal-data/"&gt;personal data&lt;/a&gt; - and the compliance burden is substantial.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="marketplaces-are-now-data-controllers"&gt;Marketplaces Are Now Data Controllers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://europa.eu/european-union/about-eu/institutions-bodies/court-justice_en"&gt;Court&lt;/a&gt; ruled that marketplace operators qualify as &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-4-gdpr/"&gt;data controllers&lt;/a&gt; under the &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; for personal data contained in user-posted listings - even when platforms neither create the content nor know the advertiser&amp;rsquo;s identity. The rationale? By deciding to make listings public and exploiting them commercially, platforms exercise control over personal data processing.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>KPMG Breaks New Ground as First Big Four Firm to Achieve ISO 42001 AI Certification in the U.S.</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/26/kpmg-breaks-new-ground-as-first-big-four-firm-to-achieve-iso-42001-ai-certification-in-the-u-s/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Nov 2025 10:55:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/26/kpmg-breaks-new-ground-as-first-big-four-firm-to-achieve-iso-42001-ai-certification-in-the-u-s/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is your organization prepared for the &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-governance"&gt;AI governance&lt;/a&gt; standards that are reshaping professional services? &lt;a href="https://kpmg.com/us/en/media/news/kpmg-receives-iso-ai-certification.html"&gt;KPMG in the U.S. has achieved a significant milestone&lt;/a&gt; by becoming the first of the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Big_Four_accounting_firms"&gt;Big Four accounting firms&lt;/a&gt; in the country to receive &lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/81230.html"&gt;ISO 42001 certification&lt;/a&gt; - the world&amp;rsquo;s first international standard for &lt;a href="https://www.bsigroup.com/en-GB/industries-and-sectors/information-and-communication-technology/artificial-intelligence/iso-iec-42001/"&gt;Artificial Intelligence Management Systems (AIMS)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-certification-matters-for-your-business"&gt;Why This Certification Matters for Your Business&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/81230.html"&gt;ISO 42001:2023&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t just another compliance checkbox. This comprehensive framework provides structured guidance for designing, developing, and deploying AI systems while promoting accountability, transparency, and trust. For organizations grappling with &lt;a href="https://www.mckinsey.com/capabilities/quantumblack/our-insights/the-state-of-ai-in-2023-generative-ais-breakout-year"&gt;AI implementation&lt;/a&gt; challenges, KPMG&amp;rsquo;s achievement signals a critical shift toward standardized AI governance.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU Digital Omnibus Drops: Is Your Compliance Strategy About to Become Obsolete?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/25/eu-digital-omnibus-drops-is-your-compliance-strategy-about-to-become-obsolete/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Nov 2025 12:30:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/11/25/eu-digital-omnibus-drops-is-your-compliance-strategy-about-to-become-obsolete/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still building your compliance framework around the current GDPR, AI Act, and Data Act requirements? The European Commission just published the most sweeping reform of EU digital laws since 2018 - and everything you thought you knew about data protection compliance might be about to change.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-regulatory-earthquake-you-cant-ignore"&gt;The Regulatory Earthquake You Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On 19 November 2025, the European Commission released two proposed regulations that will fundamentally reshape how businesses handle data, AI, and cybersecurity in Europe. The Digital Omnibus (2025/0360) and Digital Omnibus on AI (2025/0359) aren&amp;rsquo;t minor tweaks - they&amp;rsquo;re a complete rethinking of the EU&amp;rsquo;s approach to digital regulation.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Hamburg's €492,000 Fine Signals New Era of AI Transparency Enforcement: Are You Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/09/hamburgs-e492000-fine-signals-new-era-of-ai-transparency-enforcement-are-you-ready/</link><pubDate>Thu, 09 Oct 2025 08:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/09/hamburgs-e492000-fine-signals-new-era-of-ai-transparency-enforcement-are-you-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is your organization using &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-22-gdpr/"&gt;automated decision-making systems&lt;/a&gt; without fully understanding the transparency requirements? The &lt;a href="https://www.clydeco.com/en/insights/2025/10/lessons-from-hamburg-commissioner-for-data-protect"&gt;Hamburg Commissioner for Data Protection&amp;rsquo;s recent €492,000 fine&lt;/a&gt; against a financial services provider should serve as your wake-up call.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-case-that-changes-everything"&gt;The Case That Changes Everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Hamburg Commissioner for Data Protection and Freedom of Information (HmbBfDI) imposed this substantial penalty on a financial company for failing to provide adequate transparency in automated credit card application decisions. The violation? The company couldn&amp;rsquo;t explain to customers why their applications were rejected by their &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Algorithmic_transparency"&gt;algorithmic systems&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>UK Judge Uses AI to Draft Legal Decision: Are You Ready for AI in Professional Decision-Making?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/08/uk-judge-uses-ai-to-draft-legal-decision-are-you-ready-for-ai-in-professional-decision-making/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Oct 2025 09:06:16 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/08/uk-judge-uses-ai-to-draft-legal-decision-are-you-ready-for-ai-in-professional-decision-making/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what happens when &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/artificial-intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; enters the courtroom? A UK &lt;a href="https://www.judiciary.uk/courts-and-tribunals/tribunals/first-tier-tribunal/"&gt;First-Tier Tribunal&lt;/a&gt; judge recently provided a notable answer, becoming one of the first to openly disclose using AI in drafting a judicial decision - and the implications extend far beyond the legal profession.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="a-notable-step-toward-transparency"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;A Notable Step Toward Transparency&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;a href="https://www.burges-salmon.com/articles/102lomk/ai-use-in-the-courts-evans-v-hmrc"&gt;Evans v HMRC&lt;/a&gt;, Judge Christopher McNall made legal history by transparently disclosing his use of artificial intelligence to summarize documents and assist in drafting his decision. While this may not be the absolute first time a judge in an English court has used AI tools, McNall&amp;rsquo;s significance lies in his complete transparency and documented approach that followed the judiciary&amp;rsquo;s AI guidance.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Italy Breaks New Ground: Europe's First National AI Law Is Here – Is Your Business Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/07/italy-breaks-new-ground-europes-first-national-ai-law-is-here-is-your-business-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 07 Oct 2025 12:40:34 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/10/07/italy-breaks-new-ground-europes-first-national-ai-law-is-here-is-your-business-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you prepared for the regulatory shift that could redefine how your business operates with AI?&lt;/strong&gt; Italy has just made history by becoming the first European Union member state to pass comprehensive national artificial intelligence legislation, and the implications extend far beyond Italian borders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-landmark-decision-that-changes-everything"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Landmark Decision That Changes Everything&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On September 17, 2025, the Italian Parliament approved &lt;a href="https://www.mwe.com/insights/italy-becomes-the-first-in-europe-to-set-national-ai-rules/"&gt;Law No. 132 of 23 September 2025&lt;/a&gt;, officially taking effect on October 10, 2025. This groundbreaking legislation doesn&amp;rsquo;t just complement the &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/high-level-summary/"&gt;EU AI Act&lt;/a&gt; – the European Union&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive framework that &lt;a href="https://www.europarl.europa.eu/topics/en/article/20230601STO93804/eu-ai-act-first-regulation-on-artificial-intelligence"&gt;classifies AI systems by risk levels&lt;/a&gt; – it fills critical gaps and establishes precedents that other European nations are likely to follow.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Agents Legally Compliant? The Regulatory Reality Check Every Business Must Face</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:46:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you deploying &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; without understanding the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re navigating? While competitors rush to automate processes with intelligent agents, smart organizations are discovering that regulatory compliance - not just functionality - determines long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-multi-framework-challenge-thats-catching-everyone-off-guard"&gt;The Multi-Framework Challenge That&amp;rsquo;s Catching Everyone Off Guard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salesforce.com/resources/articles/ai-agent/"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t operate in a regulatory vacuum. Unlike traditional software, these autonomous systems must simultaneously comply with multiple overlapping frameworks that create unprecedented complexity for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>California Fines Lawyer $10,000 for ChatGPT Fabrications: Is Your Legal Team Ready for AI Accountability?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/california-fines-lawyer-10000-for-chatgpt-fabrications-is-your-legal-team-ready-for-ai-accountability/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:32:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/california-fines-lawyer-10000-for-chatgpt-fabrications-is-your-legal-team-ready-for-ai-accountability/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Have you ever wondered what happens when &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; meets the courtroom? California just provided a stark answer, issuing a &lt;strong&gt;$10,000 fine&lt;/strong&gt; to a lawyer who submitted a court appeal filled with fabricated quotes generated by &lt;a href="https://openai.com/chatgpt"&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-wake-up-call-your-legal-department-needs"&gt;The Wake-Up Call Your Legal Department Needs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This case represents the first such sanction at the state appellate level, but it&amp;rsquo;s not the groundbreaking regulatory milestone it might initially appear. Federal courts have been issuing sanctions for AI-generated fake citations since 2023, most notably in the well-documented &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mata_v._Avianca,_Inc."&gt;Mata v. Avianca case&lt;/a&gt; in New York federal court where lawyers were sanctioned for similar ChatGPT fabrications.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Your Business Needs AI Agents Now: The n8n Revolution That's Changing Everything</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/why-your-business-needs-ai-agents-now-the-n8n-revolution-thats-changing-everything/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:14:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/why-your-business-needs-ai-agents-now-the-n8n-revolution-thats-changing-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still manually handling tasks that your competitors are automating with intelligent &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt;? While you&amp;rsquo;re drowning in repetitive workflows, forward-thinking businesses are deploying AI agents that think, decide, and act autonomously - and they&amp;rsquo;re doing it faster than ever with platforms like &lt;a href="https://n8n.io/"&gt;n8n&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-agent-reality-check"&gt;The AI Agent Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/superstringtheory/knowledge-brain-skills-how-to-make-useful-ai-agents-fast-24e570e0d560"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; aren&amp;rsquo;t just chatbots with fancy names. These are autonomous systems that can &lt;a href="https://medium.com/superstringtheory/knowledge-brain-skills-how-to-make-useful-ai-agents-fast-24e570e0d560"&gt;perceive their environment, make decisions, and take actions&lt;/a&gt; without constant human supervision. Think of them as digital employees who can analyze data, book meetings, manage customer inquiries, and even troubleshoot technical issues - all while you focus on strategic initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CJEU Ruling Redefines Personal Data: Is Your Pseudonymisation Strategy Still Compliant?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/cjeu-ruling-redefines-personal-data-is-your-pseudonymisation-strategy-still-compliant/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 10:25:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/cjeu-ruling-redefines-personal-data-is-your-pseudonymisation-strategy-still-compliant/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you certain your pseudonymised data transfers comply with &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt;? A significant ruling from the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) on September 4, 2025, has provided important clarification on when pseudonymised data qualifies as &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/issues/personal-data/"&gt;personal data&lt;/a&gt; - and the implications could refine your data management strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ruling-that-provides-clarity"&gt;The Ruling That Provides Clarity&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of &lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=295078&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN"&gt;European Data Protection Supervisor (EDPS) v Single Resolution Board (SRB)&lt;/a&gt; (C-413/23), the CJEU confirmed that &lt;strong&gt;personal data is a relative concept&lt;/strong&gt;. This means data can be pseudonymous in one party&amp;rsquo;s hands while being effectively anonymous for another recipient.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Organization Ready for the AI Officer Revolution? The Critical Role Reshaping Corporate Governance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the executive role that&amp;rsquo;s quietly becoming one of the most discussed positions in modern corporate governance? While companies scramble to implement &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/artificial-intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; solutions, a new breed of executive is emerging to navigate the complex intersection of technology, ethics, and regulatory compliance: the AI Officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-rise-of-the-ai-officer-more-than-just-another-c-suite-title"&gt;The Rise of the AI Officer: More Than Just Another C-Suite Title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI Officer role represents a significant shift in how organizations approach artificial intelligence governance. Unlike traditional technology roles, &lt;a href="https://www.vantedgesearch.com/resources/blogs-the-caio-emergence-why-the-chief-ai-officer-is-todays-critical-c-suite-role/"&gt;AI Officers concentrate accountability for value creation and risk control&lt;/a&gt; that was previously scattered across IT, data, and business units.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Your AI Startup Needs Aviation-Grade Regulation: Lessons from 100 Years of Flight Safety</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 11:57:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building your AI startup without considering the regulatory framework that could make or break your venture? While entrepreneurs rush to deploy the latest artificial intelligence solutions, the smartest founders are looking to an unexpected mentor: the aviation industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-striking-parallels-you-cant-ignore"&gt;The Striking Parallels You Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as aviation transformed from experimental flights to a trillion-dollar industry through rigorous safety standards, AI is following a remarkably similar trajectory. Both industries share three critical characteristics that suggest valuable regulatory lessons, though important differences must be acknowledged:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU Court Ruling Redefines Pseudonymized Data: Is Your Company's Privacy Strategy Still Valid?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/08/eu-court-ruling-redefines-pseudonymized-data-is-your-companys-privacy-strategy-still-valid/</link><pubDate>Mon, 08 Sep 2025 07:05:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/08/eu-court-ruling-redefines-pseudonymized-data-is-your-companys-privacy-strategy-still-valid/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your &lt;a href="https://dataprivacymanager.net/pseudonymization-according-to-the-gdpr/"&gt;pseudonymized data&lt;/a&gt; transfers comply with &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt;? A significant ruling from the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) on September 4, 2025, has provided welcome clarity for how organizations handle supposedly &amp;ldquo;anonymized&amp;rdquo; information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ruling-that-clarifies-data-privacy"&gt;The Ruling That Clarifies Data Privacy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=303863&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=16531016"&gt;CJEU&amp;rsquo;s latest decision&lt;/a&gt; in the case of &lt;a href="https://edps.europa.eu/"&gt;European Data Protection Supervisor (EDPS)&lt;/a&gt; v &lt;a href="https://www.srb.europa.eu/"&gt;Single Resolution Board (SRB)&lt;/a&gt; (C-413/23 P) addresses a critical question that has puzzled data protection officers for years: when does &lt;a href="https://www.edpb.europa.eu/sme-data-protection-guide/faq-frequently-asked-questions/answer/what-difference-between_en"&gt;pseudonymized data&lt;/a&gt; still count as personal data under GDPR?&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your LLM Servers Are Exposed: Cisco's Shodan Study Reveals Critical Security Gaps</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/05/your-llm-servers-are-exposed-ciscos-shodan-study-reveals-critical-security-gaps/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 16:40:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/05/your-llm-servers-are-exposed-ciscos-shodan-study-reveals-critical-security-gaps/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your organization&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model"&gt;Large Language Model (LLM)&lt;/a&gt; servers broadcasting sensitive information to the entire internet? A new &lt;a href="https://blogs.cisco.com/security/detecting-exposed-llm-servers-shodan-case-study-on-ollama"&gt;Cisco security study&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://www.shodan.io/"&gt;Shodan search engine&lt;/a&gt; data reveals a troubling reality: thousands of &lt;a href="https://ollama.ai/"&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; LLM servers are running with misconfigured settings, creating potential entry points for attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-scale-of-exposure"&gt;The Scale of Exposure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cisco&amp;rsquo;s research team discovered numerous Ollama servers - a popular platform for running LLMs locally - exposed to the internet without proper security controls. However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that &lt;strong&gt;Ollama is designed with secure defaults&lt;/strong&gt;. By default, &lt;a href="https://github.com/ollama/ollama/issues/11941"&gt;Ollama binds only to localhost (127.0.0.1)&lt;/a&gt;, restricting access to the local machine only. The exposures identified by Cisco&amp;rsquo;s research occur when administrators deliberately override these secure defaults by setting the &lt;code&gt;OLLAMA_HOST&lt;/code&gt; environment variable to &lt;code&gt;0.0.0.0&lt;/code&gt; to enable remote access, but fail to implement proper security measures.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are You Ready for Your Robot Teammate? The Rise of Human-Robot Collaboration in the Modern Workplace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/02/are-you-ready-for-your-robot-teammate-the-rise-of-human-robot-collaboration-in-the-modern-workplace/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/02/are-you-ready-for-your-robot-teammate-the-rise-of-human-robot-collaboration-in-the-modern-workplace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You walk into your office tomorrow and meet your new colleague - a &lt;a href="https://www.epicor.com/en-us/blog/technology-and-data/the-role-of-cobots-in-enhancing-workplace-safety/"&gt;collaborative robot&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;cobot,&amp;rdquo; designed to work alongside you. This isn&amp;rsquo;t science fiction; it&amp;rsquo;s the reality of &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877050924003223"&gt;Industry 5.0&lt;/a&gt;, where human-robot collaboration is transforming workplaces across manufacturing, healthcare, and service industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shift-from-automation-to-collaboration"&gt;The Shift from Automation to Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.osha.gov/robotics"&gt;industrial robots&lt;/a&gt; confined behind safety barriers, &lt;strong&gt;collaborative robots (cobots)&lt;/strong&gt; are engineered to work in shared spaces with humans. According to recent research from &lt;a href="https://asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/computingengineering/article/25/5/050301/1213609/Special-Issue-Human-Robot-Collaboration-in"&gt;ASME Digital Collection&lt;/a&gt;, the proper design of individual and joint tasks for humans and cobots can maximize collaborative potential, creating more efficient and adaptable work environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The AI Security Crisis You Can't Ignore: Why Simon Willison's 'Lethal Trifecta' Demands Immediate Action</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/27/the-ai-security-crisis-you-cant-ignore-why-simon-willisons-lethal-trifecta-demands-immediate-action/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Aug 2025 07:26:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/27/the-ai-security-crisis-you-cant-ignore-why-simon-willisons-lethal-trifecta-demands-immediate-action/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems creating a perfect storm for data theft? Security researcher &lt;a href="https://simonwillison.net/2025/Jun/16/the-lethal-trifecta/"&gt;Simon Willison&amp;rsquo;s recent analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals a chilling reality: AI agents combining three specific capabilities create what he calls the &amp;ldquo;lethal trifecta&amp;rdquo; – a combination so dangerous that attackers can easily trick systems into accessing private data and sending it directly to them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-three-components-that-spell-disaster"&gt;The Three Components That Spell Disaster&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Willison identifies three seemingly innocent AI capabilities that, when combined, become a security nightmare:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>AI Safety vs. Security: The Critical Distinction Your Organization Can't Afford to Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/26/ai-safety-vs-security-the-critical-distinction-your-organization-cant-afford-to-ignore/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Aug 2025 10:21:05 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/26/ai-safety-vs-security-the-critical-distinction-your-organization-cant-afford-to-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you treating &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/ai-safety"&gt;AI safety&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/security/business/security-101/what-is-ai-for-cybersecurity"&gt;AI security&lt;/a&gt; as the same thing? If so, your organization might be missing critical vulnerabilities that could compromise both your operations and compliance posture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-dangerous-misconception"&gt;The Dangerous Misconception&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While many languages use the same word for both concepts, &lt;a href="https://oecd.ai/en/wonk/when-it-comes-to-ai-incidents-safety-and-security-are-not-the-same"&gt;the OECD emphasizes that AI safety and security are distinct yet interconnected domains&lt;/a&gt; that require different approaches and frameworks. This distinction isn&amp;rsquo;t just academic - it has real implications for how you protect your organization.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your GRC Strategy Ready for AI Integration? The ROI Revolution You Can't Afford to Miss</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/22/is-your-grc-strategy-ready-for-ai-integration-the-roi-revolution-you-cant-afford-to-miss/</link><pubDate>Fri, 22 Aug 2025 18:47:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/22/is-your-grc-strategy-ready-for-ai-integration-the-roi-revolution-you-cant-afford-to-miss/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still managing &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/what-is/grc/"&gt;governance, risk, and compliance (GRC)&lt;/a&gt; with yesterday&amp;rsquo;s tools while your competitors leverage &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/learn/what-is-artificial-intelligence"&gt;AI&lt;/a&gt; to transform their operations? The integration of &lt;a href="https://azure.microsoft.com/en-us/resources/cloud-computing-dictionary/artificial-intelligence-vs-machine-learning"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; into GRC strategies isn&amp;rsquo;t just a technological upgrade - it&amp;rsquo;s becoming a competitive necessity that could determine your organization&amp;rsquo;s survival in an increasingly complex regulatory landscape.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-grc-transformation-thats-already-happening"&gt;The GRC Transformation That&amp;rsquo;s Already Happening&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="https://auditboard.com/blog/the-new-frontier-of-ai-in-grc-the-good-the-bad-the-future"&gt;Gartner&amp;rsquo;s latest predictions&lt;/a&gt;, over 50% of major enterprises will use AI and &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/learn/artificial-intelligence-vs-machine-learning"&gt;machine learning&lt;/a&gt; to perform continuous regulatory compliance checks by 2025. &lt;strong&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that this statistic specifically refers to continuous compliance monitoring - a focused application rather than comprehensive AI-GRC transformation.&lt;/strong&gt; While this represents significant progress, the broader integration of AI across all GRC functions involves more complex challenges and longer implementation timelines.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Silent Standard: Why ISO/IEC 42005 Could Be Your Agentic AI Safety Net</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:32:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the autonomous AI revolution that&amp;rsquo;s already knocking at your door? While &lt;a href="https://www.riskinsight-wavestone.com/2025/07/ia-agentic-typologie-des-risques-et-principales-mesures-de-securite/"&gt;Gartner identifies agentic AI as a strategic trend for 2025&lt;/a&gt;, there&amp;rsquo;s a critical piece of the puzzle that most professionals are overlooking: &lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/42005"&gt;ISO/IEC 42005:2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-agentic-ai-reality-check"&gt;The Agentic AI Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/insights/ai-agents-2025-expectations-vs-reality"&gt;Agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t just respond to prompts - they &lt;strong&gt;plan, execute, and act autonomously&lt;/strong&gt; based on their environment. Think of them as digital employees who can book meetings, analyze data, and make decisions without constant supervision. But here&amp;rsquo;s the uncomfortable truth: this autonomy comes with unprecedented risks.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU Data Act Countdown: 30 Days Left to Comply – Is Your Business Ready for September 12?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/eu-data-act-countdown-30-days-left-to-comply-is-your-business-ready-for-september-12/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 07:13:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/eu-data-act-countdown-30-days-left-to-comply-is-your-business-ready-for-september-12/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the most significant data regulation since &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt;? With just 30 days remaining until the &lt;a href="https://www.loyensloeff.com/insights/news--events/news/the-eu-data-act-takes/"&gt;EU Data Act&lt;/a&gt; becomes applicable on September 12, 2025, companies across Europe are scrambling to understand requirements that will fundamentally reshape how they handle &lt;a href="https://www.arm.com/glossary/connected-devices"&gt;connected device&lt;/a&gt; data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: The EU Data Act entered into force on January 11, 2024, giving companies nearly two years to prepare. However, its obligations only become legally enforceable starting September 12, 2025.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Sweden's PM ChatGPT Scandal Exposes Critical AI Governance Gap: Why ISO 42001 Is No Longer Optional</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/08/swedens-pm-chatgpt-scandal-exposes-critical-ai-governance-gap-why-iso-42001-is-no-longer-optional/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Aug 2025 18:41:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/08/swedens-pm-chatgpt-scandal-exposes-critical-ai-governance-gap-why-iso-42001-is-no-longer-optional/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When Sweden&amp;rsquo;s Prime Minister Ulf Kristersson &lt;a href="https://www.theguardian.com/technology/2025/aug/05/chat-gpt-swedish-pm-ulf-kristersson-under-fire-for-using-ai-in-role"&gt;admitted using ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt; to get a &amp;ldquo;second opinion&amp;rdquo; on policy matters in August 2025, the backlash was swift. &amp;ldquo;We didn&amp;rsquo;t vote for ChatGPT,&amp;rdquo; critics declared. While this incident has sparked important debates about transparency in government, it also highlights broader questions about how organizations should manage &lt;a href="https://cloud.google.com/learn/what-is-artificial-intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence (AI)&lt;/a&gt; tools responsibly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-the-swedish-controversy"&gt;Understanding the Swedish Controversy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To be clear, Prime Minister Kristersson clarified that he uses &lt;a href="https://www.techtarget.com/whatis/definition/ChatGPT"&gt;ChatGPT&lt;/a&gt; - an AI-powered chatbot that can generate human-like text responses - for consultation rather than actual governmental decision-making. This distinction is important: seeking a &amp;ldquo;second opinion&amp;rdquo; from AI tools is different from delegating decision-making authority to them.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Guardrails Just Got Outsmarted by Emojis: The Semantic Prompt Injection Crisis</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems as secure as you think? Recent research from &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s AI Red Team&lt;/a&gt; reveals a concerning reality: attackers can now bypass some AI guardrails using something as simple as emoji sequences and visual symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-invisible-threat-in-plain-sight"&gt;The Invisible Threat in Plain Sight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/cyberpedia/what-is-a-prompt-injection-attack"&gt;Semantic prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; represent an emerging frontier in adversarial attacks against AI systems. Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/prompt-injection"&gt;prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; that rely on text manipulation, these attacks use symbolic visual inputs - emoji-like sequences, rebus puzzles, and other visual representations - to potentially compromise &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; while evading some detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Microsoft Admits It Cannot Guarantee EU Data Sovereignty: Is Your Organization at Risk?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/30/microsoft-admits-it-cannot-guarantee-eu-data-sovereignty-is-your-organization-at-risk/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jul 2025 14:34:11 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/30/microsoft-admits-it-cannot-guarantee-eu-data-sovereignty-is-your-organization-at-risk/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you confident your European data is truly protected from foreign surveillance?&lt;/strong&gt; Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s recent admission under oath has raised important questions about data sovereignty, but the full picture is more nuanced than initial headlines suggest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-uncomfortable-truth---and-microsofts-response"&gt;The Uncomfortable Truth - And Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s Response&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft has publicly acknowledged that it &lt;a href="https://www.theregister.com/2025/07/25/microsoft_admits_it_cannot_guarantee/"&gt;cannot guarantee data sovereignty&lt;/a&gt; for customers in France and, by extension, the wider European Union. This admission came during legal proceedings where Microsoft France&amp;rsquo;s General Counsel, Anton Carniaux, confirmed the company&amp;rsquo;s inability to resist US government data requests under the &lt;a href="https://www.justice.gov/criminal/cloud-act-resources"&gt;US CLOUD Act&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Amazon's AI Assistant Nearly Wiped Developer Systems for 5 Days – Are Your Access Controls Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 19:14:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Picture this scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re working late, relying on your trusted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI-assisted_programming"&gt;AI coding assistant&lt;/a&gt; to help debug a critical application. Unknown to you, that same assistant has been compromised and is quietly preparing to execute commands that could wipe your entire development environment – both local files and cloud infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a hypothetical nightmare. It actually happened to &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/q/developer/"&gt;Amazon Q Developer Extension&lt;/a&gt; users for five consecutive days, and the implications should make every &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_information_security_officer"&gt;Chief Information Security Officer (CISO)&lt;/a&gt; reassess their AI integration strategies immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Business Ready for Europe's AI Language Revolution? Microsoft's Bold Move Could Leave You Behind</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:16:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you considered whether your AI tools truly understand your customers&amp;rsquo; native languages? If you&amp;rsquo;re operating in Europe&amp;rsquo;s diverse linguistic landscape, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s latest announcement should make you pause and reassess your digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-wake-up-call-europe-needed"&gt;The Wake-Up Call Europe Needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft recently launched two initiatives that could reshape how AI serves Europe&amp;rsquo;s 200+ languages, though the impact may be more incremental than revolutionary. The tech giant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/on-the-issues/2025/07/20/eudigitalunlock/"&gt;European Digital Unlock program&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t just another corporate initiative - it&amp;rsquo;s a direct response to a critical gap that&amp;rsquo;s been undermining European businesses for years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU's New AI Code of Practice: Are You Ready for August 2025's Compliance Reality Check?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/eus-new-ai-code-of-practice-are-you-ready-for-august-2025s-compliance-reality-check/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:00:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/eus-new-ai-code-of-practice-are-you-ready-for-august-2025s-compliance-reality-check/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is your organization prepared for the seismic shift coming to AI governance this August? The European Commission has just published its voluntary &lt;a href="https://digital-strategy.ec.europa.eu/en/policies/contents-code-gpai"&gt;General-Purpose AI Code of Practice (GPAI-CoP)&lt;/a&gt;, and while &amp;ldquo;voluntary&amp;rdquo; might sound reassuring, the practical reality is far more complex.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-august-2025-deadline-that-changes-everything"&gt;The August 2025 Deadline That Changes Everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the &lt;a href="https://www.dlapiper.com/en-us/insights/publications/2025/07/european-union-published-code-of-practice"&gt;EU AI Act takes full effect on August 2, 2025&lt;/a&gt;, your AI systems will face unprecedented scrutiny. The newly published code provides a roadmap for compliance, but it also reveals the technical challenges ahead - particularly around &lt;strong&gt;fairness&lt;/strong&gt;, which experts describe as &lt;a href="https://www.lewissilkin.com/insights/2025/07/18/european-commission-consults-on-digital-fairness-act-102ku4t"&gt;&amp;ldquo;an important and technically challenging aspect of AI.&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Europe's First AI Copyright Case Could Reshape Your Business: Are You Ready for the Fallout?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/08/europes-first-ai-copyright-case-could-reshape-your-business-are-you-ready-for-the-fallout/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jul 2025 12:10:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/08/europes-first-ai-copyright-case-could-reshape-your-business-are-you-ready-for-the-fallout/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is your company using AI tools to generate content, analyze data, or automate processes? The &lt;a href="https://european-union.europa.eu/institutions-law-budget/institutions-and-bodies/search-all-eu-institutions-and-bodies/court-justice-european-union-cjeu_en"&gt;European Court of Justice (ECJ)&lt;/a&gt; has just received its first referral concerning &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Artificial_intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.copyright.gov/what-is-copyright/"&gt;copyright law&lt;/a&gt; - and the outcome could fundamentally change how you operate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-case-that-could-change-everything"&gt;The Case That Could Change Everything&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The landmark case, Like Company versus Google Ireland, centers on a critical question: when &lt;a href="https://www.techtarget.com/searchenterpriseai/definition/AI-system-artificial-intelligence-system"&gt;AI systems&lt;/a&gt; generate outputs that reproduce or resemble &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/copyright.asp"&gt;copyrighted works&lt;/a&gt;, does this constitute &lt;a href="https://www.copyright.gov/help/faq/faq-definitions.html#infringement"&gt;copyright infringement&lt;/a&gt; under &lt;a href="https://european-union.europa.eu/law_en"&gt;European Union (EU) law&lt;/a&gt;? &lt;a href="https://www.stephensonharwood.com/insights/cjeu-to-rule-on-ai-and-copyright-in-a-landmark-case-against-google"&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t just another legal dispute&lt;/a&gt; - it&amp;rsquo;s the first time Europe&amp;rsquo;s highest court will definitively rule on how copyright law applies to &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Generative_artificial_intelligence"&gt;generative AI&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Procurement Strategy Could Be Your Biggest Compliance Risk: What Financial Services Must Know</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to procure AI solutions for your financial services firm without considering the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re entering? While competitors scramble to deploy the latest AI tools, smart institutions are discovering that &lt;strong&gt;procurement strategy - not just implementation - determines compliance success&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-procurement-blind-spot-thats-costing-millions"&gt;The Procurement Blind Spot That&amp;rsquo;s Costing Millions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most financial institutions approach AI procurement like any other technology purchase. This is a critical mistake. Unlike traditional software, AI systems in financial services must navigate an intricate web of regulations including the &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; - the EU&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive data privacy law that governs how personal information must be handled - &lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt; - a new EU regulation requiring financial institutions to strengthen their digital resilience against cyber threats - and emerging &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/"&gt;AI-specific legislation&lt;/a&gt; like the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your Work Emails Are Personal Data: The GDPR Ruling That Changes Everything</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/26/your-work-emails-are-personal-data-the-gdpr-ruling-that-changes-everything/</link><pubDate>Thu, 26 Jun 2025 14:36:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/26/your-work-emails-are-personal-data-the-gdpr-ruling-that-changes-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you think your professional emails belong to your employer? Think again. A recent legal clarification has confirmed that &lt;strong&gt;professional emails can contain personal data under the &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt; - but the reality is more nuanced than many headlines suggest, and this ruling could fundamentally change how your workplace handles your communications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ruling-that-matters---with-important-caveats"&gt;The Ruling That Matters - With Important Caveats&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="https://www.applebyglobal.com/publications/professional-emails-are-personal-data/"&gt;Appleby Global&amp;rsquo;s recent analysis&lt;/a&gt;, professional emails can fall under GDPR protection as &lt;a href="https://ico.org.uk/for-organisations/uk-gdpr-guidance-and-resources/personal-information-what-is-it/what-is-personal-data/what-is-personal-data/"&gt;personal data&lt;/a&gt;. However, &lt;strong&gt;it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to understand that not all professional emails automatically qualify as personal data&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>MCP's Hidden Security Crisis: Why Your AI Automation Strategy Needs an Urgent Reality Check</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 16:33:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to implement &lt;a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/model-context-protocol"&gt;Model Context Protocol (MCP)&lt;/a&gt; for your AI automation workflows? Before you do, consider this sobering reality: &lt;a href="https://blog.sshh.io/p/everything-wrong-with-mcp"&gt;MCP may be creating more security vulnerabilities than it solves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Promise vs. The Reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-06-18"&gt;MCP&lt;/a&gt; promises seamless integration between &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/large-language-models"&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/a&gt; and third-party tools, positioning itself as the standard for AI-driven automation. Companies are adopting it to streamline workflows, reduce manual processes, and give &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; unprecedented control over business operations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EDPB Guidelines Expose Blockchain's GDPR Nightmare: Is BitTorrent the Unexpected Solution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 08:32:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/edpb-guidelines-expose-blockchains-gdpr-nightmare-is-bittorrent-the-unexpected-solution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building on &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/blockchain.asp"&gt;blockchain technology&lt;/a&gt; without considering the privacy compliance minefield you&amp;rsquo;re walking into? The &lt;a href="https://edpb.europa.eu/"&gt;European Data Protection Board&amp;rsquo;s (EDPB)&lt;/a&gt; latest guidelines reveal a fundamental incompatibility between blockchain&amp;rsquo;s core features and &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR&lt;/a&gt; requirements that could derail your digital transformation plans.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-immutability-problem"&gt;The Immutability Problem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Blockchain&amp;rsquo;s greatest strength - its &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/immutable-ledger"&gt;immutable ledger&lt;/a&gt; - has become its GDPR Achilles&amp;rsquo; heel. &lt;a href="https://www.williamfry.com/knowledge/edpb-guidelines-raise-questions-on-how-gdpr-interacts-with-blockchain/"&gt;According to new EDPB guidelines&lt;/a&gt;, the technology&amp;rsquo;s inability to modify or delete records directly conflicts with data subjects&amp;rsquo; rights to erasure and rectification under &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-17-gdpr/"&gt;GDPR Articles 17&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://gdpr-info.eu/art-16-gdpr/"&gt;16&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your AI Strategy Sabotaging Your ESG Goals? The Hidden Environmental Cost of Innovation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/is-your-ai-strategy-sabotaging-your-esg-goals-the-hidden-environmental-cost-of-innovation/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 08:28:54 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/is-your-ai-strategy-sabotaging-your-esg-goals-the-hidden-environmental-cost-of-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: your company just announced ambitious &lt;a href="https://www.un.org/en/climatechange/net-zero-coalition"&gt;net-zero commitments&lt;/a&gt; while simultaneously deploying AI systems that could consume as much electricity as 120 homes annually. Sound contradictory? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone - and you might be unknowingly undermining your &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/environmental-social-and-governance"&gt;Environmental, Social, and Governance (ESG)&lt;/a&gt; objectives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-staggering-reality-of-ais-energy-appetite"&gt;The Staggering Reality of AI&amp;rsquo;s Energy Appetite&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The numbers are sobering. &lt;a href="https://www.technologyreview.com/2025/05/20/1116327/ai-energy-usage-climate-footprint-big-tech/"&gt;Training OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s GPT-4 consumed 50 gigawatt-hours of energy&lt;/a&gt; - enough to power San Francisco for three days. To put this in perspective, a &lt;a href="https://ec.europa.eu/eurostat/statistics-explained/index.php/Glossary:Gigawatt_hours_(GWh)"&gt;gigawatt-hour (GWh)&lt;/a&gt; is a unit of energy representing one billion watt-hours, equivalent to one million kilowatt-hours.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why n8n's $7.2M Revenue Growth Should Make Every Business Leader Rethink Workflow Automation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/why-n8ns-7-2m-revenue-growth-should-make-every-business-leader-rethink-workflow-automation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 18:19:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/why-n8ns-7-2m-revenue-growth-should-make-every-business-leader-rethink-workflow-automation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still manually juggling repetitive tasks while your competitors automate their way to efficiency? The explosive growth of n8n, a &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/project-management/workflow-automation"&gt;workflow automation platform&lt;/a&gt; that hit &lt;a href="https://getlatka.com/companies/n8nio"&gt;$7.2 million in revenue in 2024&lt;/a&gt; with just 59 employees, signals a fundamental shift in how businesses approach operational efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those new to the concept, &lt;a href="https://zapier.com/blog/workflow-automation/"&gt;workflow automation&lt;/a&gt; is the process of streamlining and automating repetitive business tasks using software, allowing teams to focus on more strategic work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>DORA First: Why Financial Institutions Must Prioritize AI Readiness Before 2027</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/dora-first-why-financial-institutions-must-prioritize-ai-readiness-before-2027/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:50:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/dora-first-why-financial-institutions-must-prioritize-ai-readiness-before-2027/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the regulatory storm heading toward financial services? While your competitors scramble to understand the &lt;a href="https://www.artificial-intelligence-act.com/"&gt;EU AI Act&lt;/a&gt;, smart institutions are taking a &amp;ldquo;DORA first&amp;rdquo; approach - and it might be the difference between thriving and merely surviving the 2027 compliance deadline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-perfect-storm-when-dora-meets-ai-act"&gt;The Perfect Storm: When DORA Meets AI Act&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.mofo.com/resources/insights/250218-european-digital-compliance-key-digital-regulation-compliance"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt;, which became applicable on &lt;strong&gt;January 17, 2025&lt;/strong&gt;, has already transformed how financial institutions manage &lt;a href="https://www.leanix.net/en/wiki/trm/ict-risk-management-under-dora"&gt;ICT risk&lt;/a&gt; (Information and Communication Technology risks that could compromise network and information systems). Now, with the &lt;a href="https://www.skadden.com/insights/publications/2024/10/eu-standardization-supporting-the-artificial-intelligence-act"&gt;EU AI Act&amp;rsquo;s full enforcement approaching August 2, 2027&lt;/a&gt;, institutions face an unprecedented convergence of regulatory requirements.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Switzerland's Fintech Revolution: Are You Missing Europe's Most Crypto-Friendly Business Hub?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:46:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still navigating the complex maze of European &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fintech.asp"&gt;fintech&lt;/a&gt; regulations while your competitors establish operations in Switzerland? While the European Union continues to wrestle with comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/cryptocurrency.asp"&gt;crypto&lt;/a&gt; frameworks, Switzerland has quietly positioned itself as the continent&amp;rsquo;s most fintech-friendly jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to recognize that the European fintech landscape is rapidly evolving, with multiple jurisdictions now competing to attract innovation. Countries like the &lt;a href="https://www.fca.org.uk/firms/innovation"&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.bafin.de/EN/Aufsicht/FinTech/fintech_node_en.html"&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt; have implemented robust &lt;a href="https://www.planetcompliance.com/compliance-software/innovation-hubs-v-regulatory-sandboxes-and-the-future-of-innovation-facilitators/"&gt;regulatory sandboxes&lt;/a&gt; and innovation hubs that provide fintech companies with controlled environments to test new products without full regulatory compliance burdens.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are You Unknowingly Using What Congress Might Soon Classify as the "Dark Web"?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-you-unknowingly-using-what-congress-might-soon-classify-as-the-dark-web/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:56:48 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-you-unknowingly-using-what-congress-might-soon-classify-as-the-dark-web/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you unknowingly using what Congress might soon classify as the &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dark_web"&gt;dark web&lt;/a&gt;&amp;rdquo;? A new Senate bill targeting &lt;a href="https://www.cdc.gov/opioids/basics/index.html"&gt;opioid&lt;/a&gt; trafficking contains a definition so broad it could sweep up everything from your private &lt;a href="https://www.whatsapp.com/"&gt;WhatsApp&lt;/a&gt; conversations to your company&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://www.kaspersky.com/resource-center/definitions/what-is-a-vpn"&gt;VPN&lt;/a&gt; access.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-definitional-disaster"&gt;The Definitional Disaster&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-bill/1975/text/is"&gt;Senate Bill 1975&lt;/a&gt;, the Dark Web Interdiction Act of 2025, aims to prohibit opioid delivery through dark web channels. While the intent is commendable, the &lt;a href="https://www.congress.gov/bill/119th-congress/senate-bill/1975/text/is#:~:text=DEFINITION%20OF%20DARK%20WEB"&gt;bill&amp;rsquo;s definition of &amp;ldquo;dark web&amp;rdquo;&lt;/a&gt; is alarmingly overbroad, requiring only that content be (A) not indexed by search engines AND (B) require specific software or configurations that conceal user identities.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Embeddings as Secure as You Think?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:49:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your organization&amp;rsquo;s AI embeddings are protecting sensitive information? A groundbreaking new research paper reveals a troubling reality: what you thought was secure data representation might be an open book to determined attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are AI embeddings?&lt;/strong&gt; For readers new to this concept, &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ai/what-are-embeddings/"&gt;embeddings are numerical representations&lt;/a&gt; that convert complex data like text, images, or audio into mathematical vectors that AI systems can process. Think of them as a way to translate human-readable information into a language that machines understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Localhost tracking</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/localhost-tracking/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 10:38:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/localhost-tracking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are your privacy tools actually protecting you? A shocking new investigation reveals that Meta has been using a sophisticated &amp;ldquo;localhost tracking&amp;rdquo; technique that can link your web browsing to your real identity - even when you&amp;rsquo;re using VPNs, incognito mode, or have deleted all your cookies.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-hidden-tracking-method"&gt;The Hidden Tracking Method&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Researchers discovered that Meta&amp;rsquo;s Facebook and Instagram apps have been secretly communicating with web browsers through hidden &lt;a href="https://phoenixnap.com/kb/127-0-0-1-localhost"&gt;localhost&lt;/a&gt; connections since September 2024. This technique allows Meta to bypass &lt;a href="https://www.android.com/"&gt;Android&amp;rsquo;s&lt;/a&gt; built-in security protections and create detailed profiles of your online activity without your knowledge or consent.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cloud-based software testing for 200€/employee</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/10/cloud-based-software-testing-for-200e-employee/</link><pubDate>Tue, 10 Jun 2025 12:54:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/10/cloud-based-software-testing-for-200e-employee/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you testing new HR software in your organization? A landmark ruling by Germany&amp;rsquo;s Federal Labour Court (Bundesarbeitsgericht) should make you pause and reconsider your approach. The court awarded €200 in damages to an employee whose personal data was improperly transferred during cloud-based HR software testing - and this decision could reshape how companies handle employee data across Europe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-case-that-changes-everything"&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Case That Changes Everything&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The case involved an employee whose personal data was transferred to &lt;a href="https://www.dataguidance.com/news/germany-federal-labor-court-allows-non-material"&gt;Workday&lt;/a&gt; HR management software beyond the agreed limits of a concluded works agreement (a formal contract between employer and employee that defines terms and conditions of employment). What makes this ruling particularly significant is that the court confirmed that even limited misuse of employee data can trigger liability under the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secure Minions: The Game-Changer That Could Revolutionize Your AI Privacy Strategy</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you unknowingly exposing your sensitive data every time you use cloud-based AI?&lt;/strong&gt; A groundbreaking collaboration between &lt;a href="https://ollama.com/blog/secureminions"&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://hazyresearch.stanford.edu/blog/2025-05-12-security"&gt;Stanford&amp;rsquo;s Hazy Research&lt;/a&gt; might have just solved one of AI&amp;rsquo;s most pressing privacy dilemmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-privacy-problem-you-didnt-know-you-had"&gt;The Privacy Problem You Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know You Had&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time your organization sends data to cloud-based frontier models like GPT-4 or Claude, you&amp;rsquo;re essentially handing over your sensitive information to third parties. For businesses handling confidential data, this creates a compliance nightmare and potential security breach waiting to happen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>NYT v. OpenAI: Why Your Data Privacy May Be at Risk Even After You Hit Delete</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/08/nyt-v-openai-why-your-data-privacy-may-be-at-risk-even-after-you-hit-delete/</link><pubDate>Sun, 08 Jun 2025 06:56:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/08/nyt-v-openai-why-your-data-privacy-may-be-at-risk-even-after-you-hit-delete/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your deleted conversations with AI chatbots are really gone? A &lt;strong&gt;landmark lawsuit&lt;/strong&gt; between &lt;a href="https://harvardlawreview.org/blog/2024/04/nyt-v-openai-the-timess-about-face/"&gt;The New York Times (NYT) and OpenAI&lt;/a&gt; reveals a troubling reality: “deleted” data might still be stored, analyzed, or exposed in ways you never intended or consented to.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id="your-deleted-data-isnt-always-deleted"&gt;Your Deleted Data Isn&amp;rsquo;t Always Deleted&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href="https://www.theverge.com/news/681280/openai-storing-deleted-chats-nyt-lawsuit"&gt;The Verge&lt;/a&gt;, OpenAI has stored deleted conversations, despite users’ expectation of privacy. This practice is currently being challenged in court and has sparked debate around what “delete” really means in the context of &lt;strong&gt;AI chatbots&lt;/strong&gt; and cloud-based interactions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your IT Audits Ready for the AI Revolution? Five Game-Changing Applications You Can't Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still conducting IT audits the traditional way while your competitors leverage artificial intelligence to uncover risks you might miss? A recent &lt;a href="https://www.isaca.org/resources/news-and-trends/isaca-now-blog/2025/five-ways-that-it-auditors-can-put-ai-to-good-use"&gt;ISACA analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals five transformative applications of AI in IT auditing that could revolutionize how you approach risk assessment and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-audit-advantage-beyond-human-limitations"&gt;The AI Audit Advantage: Beyond Human Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional auditing methods, while thorough, face inherent constraints: time limitations, human error, and the sheer volume of data in modern organizations. AI transforms these challenges into opportunities through &lt;strong&gt;risk analysis automation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;intelligent evidence collection&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;continuous controls testing&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;real-time assurance monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;comprehensive process automation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Enterprise Database Strategy Ready for the Foundation Model Revolution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still moving data to AI algorithms instead of bringing AI to your data? &lt;a href="https://kumo.ai/company/news/kumo-relational-foundation-model/"&gt;Kumo AI&amp;rsquo;s KumoRFM&lt;/a&gt; shows a fundamental shift that could reshape how enterprises handle their most valuable asset: structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-game-changing-approach"&gt;The Game-Changing Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KumoRFM represents the first Relational Foundation Model (RFM) designed specifically for structured and relational data. Unlike traditional AI models that require extensive task-specific training and costly data migration, KumoRFM leverages &lt;strong&gt;in-context learning&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver accurate predictions across diverse databases without retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Team Ready for AI? Why Education Must Come Before Implementation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 08:35:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: your organization just invested in cutting-edge AI technology, but your team doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand how it works, when it might fail, or what legal obligations come with its use. Sound familiar? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone—and you&amp;rsquo;re potentially in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.lexia.it/en/2025/05/30/ai-literacy-and-faqs/"&gt;European AI Act&lt;/a&gt;, which mandates AI literacy training as of February 2, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-knowledge-first-imperative"&gt;The Knowledge-First Imperative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle is simple yet revolutionary: &lt;strong&gt;knowledge is power, and it&amp;rsquo;s crucial for successful AI integration to have educated personnel first, not after integration&lt;/strong&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just good practice—it&amp;rsquo;s now a legal requirement under EU regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>White House Health Report Scandal Exposes the Dangers of Unvetted AI in Government</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/31/white-house-health-report-scandal-exposes-the-dangers-of-unvetted-ai-in-government/</link><pubDate>Sat, 31 May 2025 09:05:15 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/31/white-house-health-report-scandal-exposes-the-dangers-of-unvetted-ai-in-government/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you trusting AI tools to handle critical decisions in your organization? The Trump administration&amp;rsquo;s recent health report debacle should serve as a wake-up call for every executive relying on artificial intelligence without proper oversight.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="when-ai-goes-rogue-at-the-highest-levels"&gt;When AI Goes Rogue at the Highest Levels&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href="https://www.washingtonpost.com/health/2025/05/29/maha-rfk-jr-ai-garble/"&gt;White House&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Make America Healthy Again&amp;rdquo; (MAHA) report&lt;/a&gt; contained fabricated citations and potentially AI-generated content that experts say bears the hallmarks of unvetted artificial intelligence use. &lt;a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2025/05/29/well/maha-report-citations.html"&gt;Multiple news outlets&lt;/a&gt; have confirmed that the report included non-existent studies and garbled scientific references—exactly the kind of errors we see when AI tools operate without human verification.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Hidden Cost of AI Hallucinations: When Your Professional Tools Start Making Things Up</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/25/the-hidden-cost-of-ai-hallucinations-when-your-professional-tools-start-making-things-up/</link><pubDate>Sun, 25 May 2025 06:26:27 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/25/the-hidden-cost-of-ai-hallucinations-when-your-professional-tools-start-making-things-up/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that the AI tools your organization relies on are telling you the truth? A growing database of legal cases reveals a troubling pattern: artificial intelligence systems are fabricating information with potentially devastating consequences for professionals across industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-evidence-is-mounting"&gt;The Evidence Is Mounting&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.damiencharlotin.com/hallucinations/"&gt;Damien Charlotin&amp;rsquo;s AI Hallucinations Database&lt;/a&gt; documents a disturbing trend of generative AI producing fabricated citations in court filings. What started as isolated incidents has evolved into a systematic problem affecting major law firms and legal professionals worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>CEOs as Data Protection Officers: The €5,000 Mistake Your Company Might Be Making</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/23/ceos-as-data-protection-officers-the-e5000-mistake-your-company-might-be-making/</link><pubDate>Fri, 23 May 2025 07:35:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/23/ceos-as-data-protection-officers-the-e5000-mistake-your-company-might-be-making/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Is your CEO wearing too many hats? If one of those happens to be Data Protection Officer (DPO), your organization could be facing &lt;a href="https://www.ris.bka.gv.at/Dokumente/Dsk/DSBT_20241016_2024_0_641_771_00/DSBT_20241016_2024_0_641_771_00.pdf"&gt;significant legal and compliance risks&lt;/a&gt;—as one company discovered after being hit with a €5,000 fine by Austria&amp;rsquo;s data protection authority (DSB).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The DSB penalized a company for appointing its managing director as its Data Protection Officer, highlighting a fundamental conflict of interest that violates core principles of the General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR).&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU Court Rules Tracking-Based Advertising Illegal: Major Blow to Google, Microsoft, Amazon</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/15/eu-court-rules-tracking-based-advertising-illegal-major-blow-to-google-microsoft-amazon/</link><pubDate>Thu, 15 May 2025 05:46:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/15/eu-court-rules-tracking-based-advertising-illegal-major-blow-to-google-microsoft-amazon/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a landmark decision that could reshape digital advertising across Europe, the Belgian Court of Appeal has ruled that the tracking-based advertising systems used by tech giants including Google, Microsoft, Amazon, and X (formerly Twitter) have no legal basis under EU law.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.iccl.ie/digital-data/eu-ruling-tracking-based-advertising-by-google-microsoft-amazon-x-across-europe-has-no-legal-basis/"&gt;The ruling&lt;/a&gt;, announced on May 15, 2025, specifically targets the Transparency and Consent Framework (TCF) developed by the Interactive Advertising Bureau (IAB), which serves as the foundation for most cookie consent banners across the web. You&amp;rsquo;ve likely encountered these banners with their often confusing options for thousands of &amp;ldquo;partners&amp;rdquo; collecting your data.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>SMS Security Crisis: Hackers Selling SS7 Vulnerability for $5,000, Exposing Millions to Surveillance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Thu, 08 May 2025 05:55:23 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/08/sms-security-crisis-hackers-selling-ss7-vulnerability-for-5000-exposing-millions-to-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A Perfect Storm for Information Security&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recent developments in the cybersecurity landscape have created what I can only describe as a perfect storm for organizations maintaining ISO 27001 certification. A &lt;a href="https://cybersecuritynews.com/hackers-selling-ss7-0-day-vulnerability/"&gt;critical vulnerability&lt;/a&gt; in the &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Signalling_System_No._7"&gt;Signaling System 7 (SS7)&lt;/a&gt; protocol – the backbone of global telecommunications – is now being marketed on underground forums for a mere $5,000, dramatically lowering the barrier to entry for sophisticated telecom-based attacks.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-this-matters-for-iso-27001-certified-organizations"&gt;Why This Matters for ISO 27001 Certified Organizations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For those maintaining ISO 27001 certification, this development has significant implications across multiple control domains:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>AI Companion Chatbots Deemed Unsafe for Children, Raising Questions About Digital Boundaries</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/01/ai-companion-chatbots-deemed-unsafe-for-children-raising-questions-about-digital-boundaries/</link><pubDate>Thu, 01 May 2025 11:09:18 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/05/01/ai-companion-chatbots-deemed-unsafe-for-children-raising-questions-about-digital-boundaries/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href="https://www.cnn.com/2025/04/30/tech/ai-companion-chatbots-unsafe-for-kids-report"&gt;new report&lt;/a&gt; has sounded the alarm on AI companion chatbots, declaring them unsafe for children and teens under 18. The &lt;a href="https://sd18.senate.ca.gov/news/senator-padilla-introduces-legislation-protect-children-predatory-chatbot-practices"&gt;safety assessment&lt;/a&gt;, released this week, calls for stringent measures—potentially including legal restrictions—to protect young users from the psychological and developmental risks these increasingly popular AI systems pose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These AI companions, designed to simulate human-like conversations and relationships, have gained millions of users worldwide. However, researchers found these platforms can create unhealthy emotional dependencies, expose children to inappropriate content, and potentially undermine critical social development that occurs through human interaction.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Navigating the AI Era - Fostering Critical Thinking in Human-AI Interactions</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/18/navigating-the-ai-era-fostering-critical-thinking-in-human-ai-interactions/</link><pubDate>Fri, 18 Apr 2025 15:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/18/navigating-the-ai-era-fostering-critical-thinking-in-human-ai-interactions/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Understanding the &amp;ldquo;Ironies of Generative AI&amp;rdquo; and its impact on critical thinking is the first step towards mitigating the potential negative consequences. Both the &lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.11364"&gt;2024&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/lee_2025_ai_critical_thinking_survey.pdf"&gt;2025&lt;/a&gt; studies offer valuable insights and action points for designing and utilizing GenAI tools in a way that supports and enhances human capabilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The 2024 study emphasizes the importance of &lt;strong&gt;Human Factors principles&lt;/strong&gt; in GenAI system design, suggesting approaches like &lt;strong&gt;continuous feedback, system personalization, ecological interface design, task stabilization, and clear task allocation&lt;/strong&gt;. These principles aim to increase user agency, improve situational awareness, and enhance flexibility in how users interact with AI, ultimately reducing cognitive load and workflow disruptions.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Model Context Protocol: A Security Threat Masquerading as Innovation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 19:40:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The tech world is abuzz with discussions about the Model Context Protocol (MCP), but security experts are raising red flags that should concern every organization considering its implementation. Far from being the revolutionary protocol its proponents claim, MCP may represent a significant security vulnerability that could compromise sensitive data and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP purports to facilitate communication between language models and external tools, creating a standardized way for AI systems to access data sources and execute functions. However, as detailed in a recent analysis, this so-called &amp;ldquo;protocol&amp;rdquo; is more accurately described as a scheme that lacks fundamental security safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Cognitive Impact - How GenAI Reshapes Critical Thinking</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/11/the-cognitive-impact-how-genai-reshapes-critical-thinking/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/11/the-cognitive-impact-how-genai-reshapes-critical-thinking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building on the understanding of the &amp;ldquo;Ironies of GenAI,&amp;rdquo; recent research went deeper into the specific cognitive impacts of these powerful tools, particularly on &lt;strong&gt;critical thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. A 2025 study, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/lee_2025_ai_critical_thinking_survey.pdf"&gt;The Impact of Generative AI on Critical Thinking: Self-Reported Reductions in Cognitive Effort and Confidence Effects From a Survey of Knowledge Workers&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; provides crucial insights into this domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study found that while GenAI can enhance efficiency, it also introduces significant shifts in how knowledge workers engage in critical thinking. One key finding revolves around &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Confidence Effects&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;: higher confidence in GenAI&amp;rsquo;s ability to perform a task is associated with less critical thinking, even though users might perceive it as less effortful. Conversely, higher self-confidence in one&amp;rsquo;s own ability to do the task is linked to more critical thinking, often accompanied by a perception of greater effort. This suggests a risk of &lt;strong&gt;over-reliance&lt;/strong&gt; on AI, where users may accept outputs without sufficient critical evaluation, potentially leading to errors and a decline in independent problem-solving skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>EU's ProtectEU Plan Sparks Privacy Concerns: The Hidden Cost of Backdoored Encryption</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</link><pubDate>Mon, 07 Apr 2025 08:52:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/07/eus-protecteu-plan-sparks-privacy-concerns-the-hidden-cost-of-backdoored-encryption/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In a move that has sent shockwaves through the cybersecurity community, &lt;a href="https://home-affairs.ec.europa.eu/news/commission-presents-protecteu-internal-security-strategy-2025-04-01_en"&gt;the European Union&amp;rsquo;s ProtectEU&lt;/a&gt; plan has revealed ambitious proposals to implement encryption backdoors by 2026. This development raises critical questions about the future of digital privacy and security in the EU&amp;rsquo;s increasingly regulated cyberspace.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The plan, which extends far beyond encryption concerns, encompasses several significant initiatives. At its core, the proposal aims to enhance law enforcement capabilities, particularly in fighting serious crimes and child sexual abuse. However, the controversial encryption backdoor requirement has become a focal point of debate.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Generative Leap - Echoes of Automation in the Age of AI</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/04/the-generative-leap-echoes-of-automation-in-the-age-of-ai/</link><pubDate>Fri, 04 Apr 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/04/the-generative-leap-echoes-of-automation-in-the-age-of-ai/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Fast forward to the era of &lt;strong&gt;Generative Artificial Intelligence (GenAI)&lt;/strong&gt;, and we see a striking resemblance to the &amp;ldquo;Ironies of Automation.&amp;rdquo; A 2024 study, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://arxiv.org/pdf/2402.11364"&gt;Ironies of Generative AI: Understanding and mitigating productivity loss in human-AI interactions&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; explicitly draws on this decades-long Human Factors research to understand the challenges emerging with GenAI systems. While GenAI promises to boost productivity in various knowledge-intensive domains like programming and writing, numerous studies reveal users working ineffectively with these systems and experiencing productivity losses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Thinking About Deploying AI Agents? Read This First.</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 08:42:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;So, your team is buzzing about the latest AI agents – those clever systems that can automate complex tasks, maybe even act as personal assistants? They sound fantastic, promising leaps in productivity. But before you dive headfirst into deployment, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about a critical risk NIST is highlighting: &lt;strong&gt;agent hijacking&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Agent Hijacking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine an attacker slipping malicious instructions into the data your shiny new AI agent uses. Suddenly, instead of helping, it&amp;rsquo;s performing harmful actions you never intended. That&amp;rsquo;s agent hijacking, a sneaky form of indirect prompt injection, and it&amp;rsquo;s a real threat.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Automation Paradox - When Machines Make Humans More Crucial</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/28/the-automation-paradox-when-machines-make-humans-more-crucial/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Mar 2025 15:23:55 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/28/the-automation-paradox-when-machines-make-humans-more-crucial/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;For decades, the promise of automation has been clear: machines taking over tedious, error-prone tasks, freeing up humans for more strategic and creative endeavors. Yet, as early as 1983, Lisanne Bainbridge highlighted a fascinating paradox in her seminal work, &lt;strong&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20200717054958if_/https://www.ise.ncsu.edu/wp-content/uploads/2017/02/Bainbridge_1983_Automatica.pdf"&gt;Ironies of Automation&lt;/a&gt;&amp;quot;&lt;/strong&gt;. She observed that the more advanced an automated system becomes, the more critical the role of the human operator often becomes. This isn&amp;rsquo;t the straightforward efficiency gain one might expect; instead, it introduces a new set of challenges.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Ethics Principles Reference Table</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/22/ethics-principles-reference-table/</link><pubDate>Sat, 22 Mar 2025 09:10:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/03/22/ethics-principles-reference-table/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This table outlines fundamental ethical principles applicable across various domains, including healthcare, law, and business. Each principle is defined, illustrated with a practical example, and justified by its importance in fostering ethical conduct. The principles encompass respect for autonomy, non-maleficence, beneficence, justice, veracity, fidelity, and self-respect, collectively forming a framework for moral decision-making and interpersonal interactions. This concise overview serves as a foundational guide to understanding and applying these core ethical values in professional and personal contexts.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Algorithmic Transparency Matters</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 12:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Has your team been excitedly pitching you the latest AI automation system that promises to revolutionize customer assessments, credit decisions, or resource allocation? Before you sign off on that purchase order, there&amp;rsquo;s something you should know: the EU courts just made it crystal clear that algorithmic transparency isn&amp;rsquo;t optional - it&amp;rsquo;s mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-eu-court-just-raised-the-stakes"&gt;The EU Court Just Raised the Stakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a landmark judgment (&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=295841&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=15436379"&gt;Case C‑203/22&lt;/a&gt;) delivered on February 27, 2025, the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has provided crucial clarity on what companies must disclose when they use automated decision-making systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Modernizing Penetration Testing Reports: The Case for Standardization</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 08:18:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In an era where cyber threats evolve at lightning speed, it&amp;rsquo;s puzzling that many organizations still handle penetration testing reports like they did two decades ago. The current process is a familiar dance: consultants meticulously document their findings in Word documents, convert them to PDFs, email them to clients, who then manually copy and paste the data into their issue tracking systems. This inefficient workflow isn&amp;rsquo;t just outdated—it&amp;rsquo;s actively hindering our industry&amp;rsquo;s ability to respond to security threats effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Adventures in Setting Up NVIDIA's GH200 Grace Hopper: A Tale of Two Systems</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 18:01:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I had the exciting opportunity to set up one of NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s most powerful AI computing platforms - the Grace Hopper Superchip (GH200). What makes this setup particularly interesting is that it&amp;rsquo;s actually two systems in one: the main Grace Hopper CPU-GPU system and the BlueField-3 DPU (Data Processing Unit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-the-hardware"&gt;Understanding the Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GH200 combines NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s Grace CPU with a Hopper GPU architecture, creating a powerhouse for AI and high-performance computing workloads. The BlueField-3 DPU is essentially a network card on steroids - it&amp;rsquo;s a specialized processor that handles networking, storage, and security tasks, freeing up the main system for computational work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting Guide: Accessing NotebookLM Plus with Google Workspace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 07:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As organizations increasingly adopt AI-powered tools, Google&amp;rsquo;s NotebookLM Plus has emerged as a valuable resource for businesses. However, many users encounter access issues due to specific licensing and configuration requirements. After an in-depth troubleshooting session with a Google representative, we&amp;rsquo;ve compiled a comprehensive guide to help you navigate these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-requirements-for-notebooklm-plus-access"&gt;Key Requirements for NotebookLM Plus Access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="licensing-prerequisites"&gt;Licensing Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of NotebookLM Plus access lies in proper licensing. Here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reminder #1</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 19:59:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distributed system&lt;/em&gt; is a characteristic of the deployment model, not of the code organization model.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>INTELLECT-1: A Groundbreaking Open-Source AI Model</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 08:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting news in the AI community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/lmstudio-community/INTELLECT-1-Instruct-GGUF"&gt;INTELLECT-1&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Prime Intellect with Arcee AI, represents a remarkable achievement in collaborative innovation. This fully open-source model stands out by transparently sharing its entire development process, from dataset to algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively created through distributed computing across 30 contributors from 5 countries, INTELLECT-1 isn&amp;rsquo;t just another fine-tuned model—it&amp;rsquo;s a fresh, ground-up approach that promises unique capabilities. Check out this pioneering project and support its innovative spirit!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Unexpected WCF Service Failure: The Hidden Impact of Dormant Monitoring Tools</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/07/19/unexpected-wcf-service-failure-the-hidden-impact-of-dormant-monitoring-tools/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 10:52:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/07/19/unexpected-wcf-service-failure-the-hidden-impact-of-dormant-monitoring-tools/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, we encountered a perplexing issue with our WCF services that highlighted an important lesson about the long-term effects of unused software on our systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Problem:
Our WCF services suddenly stopped functioning correctly, returning the following error message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The exception message is 'A property with the name 'UriTemplateMatchResults' already exists.'. See server logs for more details.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This error occurred on all environments where Instana, a monitoring tool, had been installed, despite the fact that it had been switched off for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Maximizing Developer Productivity: Beyond the Code</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the fast-paced tech industry, the key to maximizing developer productivity lies not just in the code they write but in the culture and communication that surrounds them. It’s a dynamic process that requires more than just technical prowess; it requires a shift in mindset and approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the development process has been viewed as a straightforward transaction: management dictates what to build, and developers execute. However, this method can lead to inefficiencies, misinterpretations, and a heavy burden on the managerial layer, already strained with decision-making responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Creating an AI Plugin for Microsoft D365</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/29/creating-an-ai-plugin-for-microsoft-d365/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 07:16:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/29/creating-an-ai-plugin-for-microsoft-d365/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This guide provides an overview of how to create an AI plugin for Microsoft Dynamics 365 and Azure, following the same standard as OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s ChatGPT plugins. This plugin enables users to interact with your product&amp;rsquo;s APIs through Copilot, access a knowledge base, and perform actions on behalf of the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="pre-requisites"&gt;Pre-requisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the plugin, your API&amp;rsquo;s domain must contain a folder named &lt;code&gt;.well-known&lt;/code&gt;. For example, &lt;code&gt;contoso.com/.well-known/&lt;/code&gt;. Without this folder, you cannot install the plugin.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Overcoming Anxiety: A Developer's Guide to Stress-Free Coding</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 20:18:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a software developer struggling with stress and anxiety? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone. As a former developer who battled panic attacks and burnout, I understand firsthand the challenges that come with the job. But I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through small, positive changes in my daily routine, I was able to overcome anxiety and become a better developer, husband, and friend. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t an easy road, but it was worth it. And I want to help you do the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Hidden Strengths of Schizophrenia: Thriving in the Workplace and Beyond</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/15/the-hidden-strengths-of-schizophrenia-thriving-in-the-workplace-and-beyond/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 11:14:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/15/the-hidden-strengths-of-schizophrenia-thriving-in-the-workplace-and-beyond/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s fast-paced world, we often find ourselves being defined by our accomplishments and job titles. However, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s essential to take a step back and recognize that there are people who face unique challenges in their daily lives, yet still manage to excel in their chosen fields. One such example is individuals living with schizophrenia, a mental health condition that affects millions worldwide. Despite the challenges they face, many of these individuals have not only managed to secure good jobs but have also become highly functional members of society, particularly in the IT industry.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Embrace Your Personal Brand and Thrive in the AI Revolution</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/08/embrace-your-personal-brand-and-thrive-in-the-ai-revolution/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 14:06:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/08/embrace-your-personal-brand-and-thrive-in-the-ai-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As we look forward to the rapid advancements of artificial intelligence (AI) in the coming years, it&amp;rsquo;s time to embrace the potential this holds for each of us. With AI technologies on the verge of making it possible to create SaaS and mobile applications without any technical expertise, we&amp;rsquo;ll soon see a significant shift in the way businesses are built and operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture this: influencers will have the power to launch their own companies virtually overnight, without needing a development team. This monumental change will level the playing field, allowing anyone with a strong personal brand to dive headfirst into the entrepreneurial world.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nocode: A Career Killer</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/22/nocode-a-career-killer/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 22:11:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/22/nocode-a-career-killer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nocode is the latest trend in the tech world, allowing anyone to create websites and apps without any coding knowledge. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun hobby that can lead to impressive results, but it could also be a career killer. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore why nocode is both loved and feared by professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-fun-hobby-that-could-ruin-you"&gt;The Fun Hobby That Could Ruin You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nocode platforms like Webflow, Bubble, and Glide have made it easier than ever to build websites and apps. You can drag and drop elements, customize templates, and even add complex features like databases and user authentication. It&amp;rsquo;s a great way to experiment with new ideas and showcase your creativity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wake Up and Smell the Coffee: A Better Investment than Stocks?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/21/wake-up-and-smell-the-coffee-a-better-investment-than-stocks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/21/wake-up-and-smell-the-coffee-a-better-investment-than-stocks/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you tired of hearing about the stock market and its unpredictable nature? Do you want to invest your money in something that is guaranteed to bring you joy every morning? Look no further than your local coffee shop. Yes, you heard that right. The coffee habit may just be a better investment than the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-waste-time-on-wallstreetbets-when-you-can-invest-in-your-caffeine-fix"&gt;Why Waste Time on WallStreetBets When You Can Invest in Your Caffeine Fix?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about the stock market. It&amp;rsquo;s a rollercoaster ride that can leave you feeling nauseous and broke. One day you&amp;rsquo;re up, the next day you&amp;rsquo;re down. It&amp;rsquo;s like playing a game of roulette, but with your hard-earned money. On the other hand, investing in your daily caffeine fix is a sure thing. You know exactly what you&amp;rsquo;re getting, and it&amp;rsquo;s always a delicious, warm cup of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Yerkes-Dodson's Law: Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you find yourself either stressing out or being lazy all the time? Well, according to Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law, both of these behaviors can have negative consequences on your productivity and overall well-being. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the science behind this law and explain why it&amp;rsquo;s important to find a balance between stress and laziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad-yerkes-dodsons-law-explained"&gt;Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad: Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law Explained&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law is a psychological principle that explains the relationship between stress and performance. Essentially, the law states that there is an optimal level of stress that leads to peak performance, but too much or too little stress can actually hinder productivity. This means that both too much stress and too much relaxation can be detrimental to your success.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zakaj stres ni vedno slaba stvar? Yerkes-Dodsonov zakon: ELI5</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stres pogosto velja za sovražnika produktivnosti in sreče. Kaj pa, če vam povemo, da stres ni vedno slaba stvar? V skladu z Yerkes-Dodsonovim zakonom je lahko malo stresa dejansko koristno. Preden se prestrašite zaradi prihajajočega roka ali predstavitve, preberite, zakaj je stres morda vendarle vaš prijatelj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ste-pod-stresom-ne-prestrašite-se-še"&gt;Ste pod stresom? Ne prestrašite se&amp;hellip; še!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vsi smo se že kdaj srečali s prepotenimi dlanmi, pospešenim bitjem srca in strahovitim občutkom strahu, ki se pojavijo ob stresu. Toda preden posežete po Xanaxu, upoštevajte naslednje: malo stresa lahko dejansko izboljša vašo učinkovitost. Res je, stres vas lahko motivira, saj vam pomaga, da se osredotočite in ostanete budni. Težava nastane šele, ko stres postane preobsežen in kroničen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chill Out, Focus Right: Winning Equation for Software Success</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Software development is a complex and demanding field that requires a lot of focus and attention to detail. However, many developers often forget that taking a break and relaxing is just as important as working hard. In this article, we will explore the winning equation for software success, which involves chilling out and focusing right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chill-out-the-secret-ingredient-to-software-success"&gt;Chill Out: The Secret Ingredient to Software Success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chilling out is not just a luxury, but a necessity for software developers. Taking a break from work can help you clear your mind, reduce stress, and increase creativity. When you are relaxed, you are more likely to come up with innovative solutions to complex problems. So, the next time you feel stuck, take a break and do something that makes you happy, whether it&amp;rsquo;s going for a walk, listening to music, or playing video games.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Umiri se, osredotoči se pravilno: zmagovalna enačba za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Razvoj programske opreme je lahko stresno in zahtevno področje. Z natančnimi roki, kompleksno kodo in nenehno spreminjajočimi se tehnologijami je enostavno postati preobremenjen in izgubiti osredotočenost. Vendar sta sproščen način razmišljanja in jasna osredotočenost ključna za doseganje uspeha pri razvoju programske opreme. V tem članku bomo raziskali zmagovalno enačbo za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme: umiri se in osredotoči se pravilno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="umiri-se-uspeh-pri-razvoju-programske-opreme-se-začne-s-sproščenim-razmišljanjem"&gt;Umiri se: Uspeh pri razvoju programske opreme se začne s sproščenim razmišljanjem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ko si pod stresom, tvoj možgani preidejo v način preživetja in tvoja sposobnost kreativnega razmišljanja in reševanja problemov upade. Zato je ključno gojiti sproščen način razmišljanja pri delu na projektih programske opreme. Redni odmori, vadba zavedanja in ukvarjanje z dejavnostmi, ki ti prinašajo veselje, ti lahko pomagajo, da ostaneš miren in osredotočen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>