<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Audit on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/audit/</link><description>Recent content in Audit on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:32:47 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/audit/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>The Silent Standard: Why ISO/IEC 42005 Could Be Your Agentic AI Safety Net</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</link><pubDate>Thu, 14 Aug 2025 09:32:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/14/the-silent-standard-why-iso-iec-42005-could-be-your-agentic-ai-safety-net/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the autonomous AI revolution that&amp;rsquo;s already knocking at your door? While &lt;a href="https://www.riskinsight-wavestone.com/2025/07/ia-agentic-typologie-des-risques-et-principales-mesures-de-securite/"&gt;Gartner identifies agentic AI as a strategic trend for 2025&lt;/a&gt;, there&amp;rsquo;s a critical piece of the puzzle that most professionals are overlooking: &lt;a href="https://www.iso.org/standard/42005"&gt;ISO/IEC 42005:2025&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-agentic-ai-reality-check"&gt;The Agentic AI Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/insights/ai-agents-2025-expectations-vs-reality"&gt;Agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t just respond to prompts - they &lt;strong&gt;plan, execute, and act autonomously&lt;/strong&gt; based on their environment. Think of them as digital employees who can book meetings, analyze data, and make decisions without constant supervision. But here&amp;rsquo;s the uncomfortable truth: this autonomy comes with unprecedented risks.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Amazon's AI Assistant Nearly Wiped Developer Systems for 5 Days – Are Your Access Controls Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 19:14:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Picture this scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re working late, relying on your trusted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI-assisted_programming"&gt;AI coding assistant&lt;/a&gt; to help debug a critical application. Unknown to you, that same assistant has been compromised and is quietly preparing to execute commands that could wipe your entire development environment – both local files and cloud infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a hypothetical nightmare. It actually happened to &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/q/developer/"&gt;Amazon Q Developer Extension&lt;/a&gt; users for five consecutive days, and the implications should make every &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_information_security_officer"&gt;Chief Information Security Officer (CISO)&lt;/a&gt; reassess their AI integration strategies immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Procurement Strategy Could Be Your Biggest Compliance Risk: What Financial Services Must Know</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to procure AI solutions for your financial services firm without considering the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re entering? While competitors scramble to deploy the latest AI tools, smart institutions are discovering that &lt;strong&gt;procurement strategy - not just implementation - determines compliance success&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-procurement-blind-spot-thats-costing-millions"&gt;The Procurement Blind Spot That&amp;rsquo;s Costing Millions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most financial institutions approach AI procurement like any other technology purchase. This is a critical mistake. Unlike traditional software, AI systems in financial services must navigate an intricate web of regulations including the &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; - the EU&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive data privacy law that governs how personal information must be handled - &lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt; - a new EU regulation requiring financial institutions to strengthen their digital resilience against cyber threats - and emerging &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/"&gt;AI-specific legislation&lt;/a&gt; like the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Embeddings as Secure as You Think?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:49:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your organization&amp;rsquo;s AI embeddings are protecting sensitive information? A groundbreaking new research paper reveals a troubling reality: what you thought was secure data representation might be an open book to determined attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are AI embeddings?&lt;/strong&gt; For readers new to this concept, &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ai/what-are-embeddings/"&gt;embeddings are numerical representations&lt;/a&gt; that convert complex data like text, images, or audio into mathematical vectors that AI systems can process. Think of them as a way to translate human-readable information into a language that machines understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secure Minions: The Game-Changer That Could Revolutionize Your AI Privacy Strategy</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</link><pubDate>Mon, 09 Jun 2025 10:34:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/09/secure-minions-the-game-changer-that-could-revolutionize-your-ai-privacy-strategy/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Are you unknowingly exposing your sensitive data every time you use cloud-based AI?&lt;/strong&gt; A groundbreaking collaboration between &lt;a href="https://ollama.com/blog/secureminions"&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://hazyresearch.stanford.edu/blog/2025-05-12-security"&gt;Stanford&amp;rsquo;s Hazy Research&lt;/a&gt; might have just solved one of AI&amp;rsquo;s most pressing privacy dilemmas.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-privacy-problem-you-didnt-know-you-had"&gt;The Privacy Problem You Didn&amp;rsquo;t Know You Had&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every time your organization sends data to cloud-based frontier models like GPT-4 or Claude, you&amp;rsquo;re essentially handing over your sensitive information to third parties. For businesses handling confidential data, this creates a compliance nightmare and potential security breach waiting to happen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your IT Audits Ready for the AI Revolution? Five Game-Changing Applications You Can't Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still conducting IT audits the traditional way while your competitors leverage artificial intelligence to uncover risks you might miss? A recent &lt;a href="https://www.isaca.org/resources/news-and-trends/isaca-now-blog/2025/five-ways-that-it-auditors-can-put-ai-to-good-use"&gt;ISACA analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals five transformative applications of AI in IT auditing that could revolutionize how you approach risk assessment and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-audit-advantage-beyond-human-limitations"&gt;The AI Audit Advantage: Beyond Human Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional auditing methods, while thorough, face inherent constraints: time limitations, human error, and the sheer volume of data in modern organizations. AI transforms these challenges into opportunities through &lt;strong&gt;risk analysis automation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;intelligent evidence collection&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;continuous controls testing&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;real-time assurance monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;comprehensive process automation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>