<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Happiness on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/happiness/</link><description>Recent content in Happiness on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 20:18:22 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Overcoming Anxiety: A Developer's Guide to Stress-Free Coding</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 20:18:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a software developer struggling with stress and anxiety? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone. As a former developer who battled panic attacks and burnout, I understand firsthand the challenges that come with the job. But I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through small, positive changes in my daily routine, I was able to overcome anxiety and become a better developer, husband, and friend. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t an easy road, but it was worth it. And I want to help you do the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Hidden Strengths of Schizophrenia: Thriving in the Workplace and Beyond</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/15/the-hidden-strengths-of-schizophrenia-thriving-in-the-workplace-and-beyond/</link><pubDate>Sat, 15 Apr 2023 11:14:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/15/the-hidden-strengths-of-schizophrenia-thriving-in-the-workplace-and-beyond/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In today&amp;rsquo;s fast-paced world, we often find ourselves being defined by our accomplishments and job titles. However, sometimes it&amp;rsquo;s essential to take a step back and recognize that there are people who face unique challenges in their daily lives, yet still manage to excel in their chosen fields. One such example is individuals living with schizophrenia, a mental health condition that affects millions worldwide. Despite the challenges they face, many of these individuals have not only managed to secure good jobs but have also become highly functional members of society, particularly in the IT industry.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Wake Up and Smell the Coffee: A Better Investment than Stocks?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/21/wake-up-and-smell-the-coffee-a-better-investment-than-stocks/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Mar 2023 22:09:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/21/wake-up-and-smell-the-coffee-a-better-investment-than-stocks/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you tired of hearing about the stock market and its unpredictable nature? Do you want to invest your money in something that is guaranteed to bring you joy every morning? Look no further than your local coffee shop. Yes, you heard that right. The coffee habit may just be a better investment than the stock market.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-waste-time-on-wallstreetbets-when-you-can-invest-in-your-caffeine-fix"&gt;Why Waste Time on WallStreetBets When You Can Invest in Your Caffeine Fix?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Firstly, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about the stock market. It&amp;rsquo;s a rollercoaster ride that can leave you feeling nauseous and broke. One day you&amp;rsquo;re up, the next day you&amp;rsquo;re down. It&amp;rsquo;s like playing a game of roulette, but with your hard-earned money. On the other hand, investing in your daily caffeine fix is a sure thing. You know exactly what you&amp;rsquo;re getting, and it&amp;rsquo;s always a delicious, warm cup of happiness.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chill Out, Focus Right: Winning Equation for Software Success</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Software development is a complex and demanding field that requires a lot of focus and attention to detail. However, many developers often forget that taking a break and relaxing is just as important as working hard. In this article, we will explore the winning equation for software success, which involves chilling out and focusing right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chill-out-the-secret-ingredient-to-software-success"&gt;Chill Out: The Secret Ingredient to Software Success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chilling out is not just a luxury, but a necessity for software developers. Taking a break from work can help you clear your mind, reduce stress, and increase creativity. When you are relaxed, you are more likely to come up with innovative solutions to complex problems. So, the next time you feel stuck, take a break and do something that makes you happy, whether it&amp;rsquo;s going for a walk, listening to music, or playing video games.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Umiri se, osredotoči se pravilno: zmagovalna enačba za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Razvoj programske opreme je lahko stresno in zahtevno področje. Z natančnimi roki, kompleksno kodo in nenehno spreminjajočimi se tehnologijami je enostavno postati preobremenjen in izgubiti osredotočenost. Vendar sta sproščen način razmišljanja in jasna osredotočenost ključna za doseganje uspeha pri razvoju programske opreme. V tem članku bomo raziskali zmagovalno enačbo za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme: umiri se in osredotoči se pravilno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="umiri-se-uspeh-pri-razvoju-programske-opreme-se-začne-s-sproščenim-razmišljanjem"&gt;Umiri se: Uspeh pri razvoju programske opreme se začne s sproščenim razmišljanjem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ko si pod stresom, tvoj možgani preidejo v način preživetja in tvoja sposobnost kreativnega razmišljanja in reševanja problemov upade. Zato je ključno gojiti sproščen način razmišljanja pri delu na projektih programske opreme. Redni odmori, vadba zavedanja in ukvarjanje z dejavnostmi, ki ti prinašajo veselje, ti lahko pomagajo, da ostaneš miren in osredotočen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>