<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Team on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/team/</link><description>Recent content in Team on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:30:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/categories/team/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Is Your Organization Ready for the AI Officer Revolution? The Critical Role Reshaping Corporate Governance</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</link><pubDate>Mon, 22 Sep 2025 10:30:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/22/is-your-organization-ready-for-the-ai-officer-revolution-the-critical-role-reshaping-corporate-governance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you prepared for the executive role that&amp;rsquo;s quietly becoming one of the most discussed positions in modern corporate governance? While companies scramble to implement &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/artificial-intelligence"&gt;artificial intelligence&lt;/a&gt; solutions, a new breed of executive is emerging to navigate the complex intersection of technology, ethics, and regulatory compliance: the AI Officer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-rise-of-the-ai-officer-more-than-just-another-c-suite-title"&gt;The Rise of the AI Officer: More Than Just Another C-Suite Title&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The AI Officer role represents a significant shift in how organizations approach artificial intelligence governance. Unlike traditional technology roles, &lt;a href="https://www.vantedgesearch.com/resources/blogs-the-caio-emergence-why-the-chief-ai-officer-is-todays-critical-c-suite-role/"&gt;AI Officers concentrate accountability for value creation and risk control&lt;/a&gt; that was previously scattered across IT, data, and business units.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Team Ready for AI? Why Education Must Come Before Implementation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 02 Jun 2025 08:35:28 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/02/is-your-team-ready-for-ai-why-education-must-come-before-implementation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: your organization just invested in cutting-edge AI technology, but your team doesn&amp;rsquo;t understand how it works, when it might fail, or what legal obligations come with its use. Sound familiar? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone—and you&amp;rsquo;re potentially in violation of the &lt;a href="https://www.lexia.it/en/2025/05/30/ai-literacy-and-faqs/"&gt;European AI Act&lt;/a&gt;, which mandates AI literacy training as of February 2, 2025.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-knowledge-first-imperative"&gt;The Knowledge-First Imperative&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The principle is simple yet revolutionary: &lt;strong&gt;knowledge is power, and it&amp;rsquo;s crucial for successful AI integration to have educated personnel first, not after integration&lt;/strong&gt;. This isn&amp;rsquo;t just good practice—it&amp;rsquo;s now a legal requirement under EU regulations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Cognitive Impact - How GenAI Reshapes Critical Thinking</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/11/the-cognitive-impact-how-genai-reshapes-critical-thinking/</link><pubDate>Fri, 11 Apr 2025 15:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/11/the-cognitive-impact-how-genai-reshapes-critical-thinking/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Building on the understanding of the &amp;ldquo;Ironies of GenAI,&amp;rdquo; recent research went deeper into the specific cognitive impacts of these powerful tools, particularly on &lt;strong&gt;critical thinking&lt;/strong&gt;. A 2025 study, &amp;ldquo;&lt;a href="https://www.microsoft.com/en-us/research/wp-content/uploads/2025/01/lee_2025_ai_critical_thinking_survey.pdf"&gt;The Impact of Generative AI on Critical Thinking: Self-Reported Reductions in Cognitive Effort and Confidence Effects From a Survey of Knowledge Workers&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;rdquo; provides crucial insights into this domain.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The study found that while GenAI can enhance efficiency, it also introduces significant shifts in how knowledge workers engage in critical thinking. One key finding revolves around &lt;strong&gt;&amp;ldquo;Confidence Effects&amp;rdquo;&lt;/strong&gt;: higher confidence in GenAI&amp;rsquo;s ability to perform a task is associated with less critical thinking, even though users might perceive it as less effortful. Conversely, higher self-confidence in one&amp;rsquo;s own ability to do the task is linked to more critical thinking, often accompanied by a perception of greater effort. This suggests a risk of &lt;strong&gt;over-reliance&lt;/strong&gt; on AI, where users may accept outputs without sufficient critical evaluation, potentially leading to errors and a decline in independent problem-solving skills.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Troubleshooting Guide: Accessing NotebookLM Plus with Google Workspace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Feb 2025 07:39:52 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/08/troubleshooting-guide-accessing-notebooklm-plus-with-google-workspace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As organizations increasingly adopt AI-powered tools, Google&amp;rsquo;s NotebookLM Plus has emerged as a valuable resource for businesses. However, many users encounter access issues due to specific licensing and configuration requirements. After an in-depth troubleshooting session with a Google representative, we&amp;rsquo;ve compiled a comprehensive guide to help you navigate these requirements.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="key-requirements-for-notebooklm-plus-access"&gt;Key Requirements for NotebookLM Plus Access&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h3 id="licensing-prerequisites"&gt;Licensing Prerequisites&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The foundation of NotebookLM Plus access lies in proper licensing. Here&amp;rsquo;s what you need to know:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Maximizing Developer Productivity: Beyond the Code</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the fast-paced tech industry, the key to maximizing developer productivity lies not just in the code they write but in the culture and communication that surrounds them. It’s a dynamic process that requires more than just technical prowess; it requires a shift in mindset and approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the development process has been viewed as a straightforward transaction: management dictates what to build, and developers execute. However, this method can lead to inefficiencies, misinterpretations, and a heavy burden on the managerial layer, already strained with decision-making responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Yerkes-Dodson's Law: Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you find yourself either stressing out or being lazy all the time? Well, according to Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law, both of these behaviors can have negative consequences on your productivity and overall well-being. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the science behind this law and explain why it&amp;rsquo;s important to find a balance between stress and laziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad-yerkes-dodsons-law-explained"&gt;Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad: Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law Explained&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law is a psychological principle that explains the relationship between stress and performance. Essentially, the law states that there is an optimal level of stress that leads to peak performance, but too much or too little stress can actually hinder productivity. This means that both too much stress and too much relaxation can be detrimental to your success.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zakaj stres ni vedno slaba stvar? Yerkes-Dodsonov zakon: ELI5</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stres pogosto velja za sovražnika produktivnosti in sreče. Kaj pa, če vam povemo, da stres ni vedno slaba stvar? V skladu z Yerkes-Dodsonovim zakonom je lahko malo stresa dejansko koristno. Preden se prestrašite zaradi prihajajočega roka ali predstavitve, preberite, zakaj je stres morda vendarle vaš prijatelj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ste-pod-stresom-ne-prestrašite-se-še"&gt;Ste pod stresom? Ne prestrašite se&amp;hellip; še!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vsi smo se že kdaj srečali s prepotenimi dlanmi, pospešenim bitjem srca in strahovitim občutkom strahu, ki se pojavijo ob stresu. Toda preden posežete po Xanaxu, upoštevajte naslednje: malo stresa lahko dejansko izboljša vašo učinkovitost. Res je, stres vas lahko motivira, saj vam pomaga, da se osredotočite in ostanete budni. Težava nastane šele, ko stres postane preobsežen in kroničen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>