<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Software Development on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/software-development/</link><description>Recent content in Software Development on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:46:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/software-development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Are Your AI Agents Legally Compliant? The Regulatory Reality Check Every Business Must Face</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</link><pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 08:46:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/26/are-your-ai-agents-legally-compliant-the-regulatory-reality-check-every-business-must-face/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you deploying &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; without understanding the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re navigating? While competitors rush to automate processes with intelligent agents, smart organizations are discovering that regulatory compliance - not just functionality - determines long-term success.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-multi-framework-challenge-thats-catching-everyone-off-guard"&gt;The Multi-Framework Challenge That&amp;rsquo;s Catching Everyone Off Guard&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.salesforce.com/resources/articles/ai-agent/"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t operate in a regulatory vacuum. Unlike traditional software, these autonomous systems must simultaneously comply with multiple overlapping frameworks that create unprecedented complexity for businesses.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Post-Quantum Cryptography: Why the Threat is Already Here</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</link><pubDate>Mon, 04 Aug 2025 10:55:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/04/post-quantum-cryptography-why-the-threat-is-already-here/</guid><description>&lt;h2 id="a-practical-guide-for-infosec-professionals-and-auditors"&gt;A Practical Guide for InfoSec Professionals and Auditors&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As someone working daily with ISO standards and AI governance frameworks, I&amp;rsquo;ve been closely following NIST&amp;rsquo;s post-quantum cryptography (PQC) standardization process. What I&amp;rsquo;ve discovered should concern every InfoSec professional: the threat to our current encryption isn&amp;rsquo;t waiting for some hypothetical quantum computer. It&amp;rsquo;s already growing in GPU farms around the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this guide, I&amp;rsquo;ll break down what you need to know about post-quantum cryptography without the complex mathematics. More importantly, I&amp;rsquo;ll explain why this matters for your organization today, not in some distant quantum future.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Guardrails Just Got Outsmarted by Emojis: The Semantic Prompt Injection Crisis</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems as secure as you think? Recent research from &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s AI Red Team&lt;/a&gt; reveals a concerning reality: attackers can now bypass some AI guardrails using something as simple as emoji sequences and visual symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-invisible-threat-in-plain-sight"&gt;The Invisible Threat in Plain Sight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/cyberpedia/what-is-a-prompt-injection-attack"&gt;Semantic prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; represent an emerging frontier in adversarial attacks against AI systems. Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/prompt-injection"&gt;prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; that rely on text manipulation, these attacks use symbolic visual inputs - emoji-like sequences, rebus puzzles, and other visual representations - to potentially compromise &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; while evading some detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your AI Embeddings as Secure as You Think?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</link><pubDate>Thu, 12 Jun 2025 15:49:06 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/12/are-your-ai-embeddings-as-secure-as-you-think/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you confident that your organization&amp;rsquo;s AI embeddings are protecting sensitive information? A groundbreaking new research paper reveals a troubling reality: what you thought was secure data representation might be an open book to determined attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What are AI embeddings?&lt;/strong&gt; For readers new to this concept, &lt;a href="https://www.cloudflare.com/learning/ai/what-are-embeddings/"&gt;embeddings are numerical representations&lt;/a&gt; that convert complex data like text, images, or audio into mathematical vectors that AI systems can process. Think of them as a way to translate human-readable information into a language that machines understand.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Enterprise Database Strategy Ready for the Foundation Model Revolution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still moving data to AI algorithms instead of bringing AI to your data? &lt;a href="https://kumo.ai/company/news/kumo-relational-foundation-model/"&gt;Kumo AI&amp;rsquo;s KumoRFM&lt;/a&gt; shows a fundamental shift that could reshape how enterprises handle their most valuable asset: structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-game-changing-approach"&gt;The Game-Changing Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KumoRFM represents the first Relational Foundation Model (RFM) designed specifically for structured and relational data. Unlike traditional AI models that require extensive task-specific training and costly data migration, KumoRFM leverages &lt;strong&gt;in-context learning&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver accurate predictions across diverse databases without retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Model Context Protocol: A Security Threat Masquerading as Innovation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 19:40:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The tech world is abuzz with discussions about the Model Context Protocol (MCP), but security experts are raising red flags that should concern every organization considering its implementation. Far from being the revolutionary protocol its proponents claim, MCP may represent a significant security vulnerability that could compromise sensitive data and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP purports to facilitate communication between language models and external tools, creating a standardized way for AI systems to access data sources and execute functions. However, as detailed in a recent analysis, this so-called &amp;ldquo;protocol&amp;rdquo; is more accurately described as a scheme that lacks fundamental security safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Thinking About Deploying AI Agents? Read This First.</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 08:42:04 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/02/thinking-about-deploying-ai-agents-read-this-first/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;So, your team is buzzing about the latest AI agents – those clever systems that can automate complex tasks, maybe even act as personal assistants? They sound fantastic, promising leaps in productivity. But before you dive headfirst into deployment, let&amp;rsquo;s talk about a critical risk NIST is highlighting: &lt;strong&gt;agent hijacking&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;What&amp;rsquo;s Agent Hijacking?&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Imagine an attacker slipping malicious instructions into the data your shiny new AI agent uses. Suddenly, instead of helping, it&amp;rsquo;s performing harmful actions you never intended. That&amp;rsquo;s agent hijacking, a sneaky form of indirect prompt injection, and it&amp;rsquo;s a real threat.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Algorithmic Transparency Matters</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</link><pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2025 12:35:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/28/why-algorithmic-transparency-matters/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Has your team been excitedly pitching you the latest AI automation system that promises to revolutionize customer assessments, credit decisions, or resource allocation? Before you sign off on that purchase order, there&amp;rsquo;s something you should know: the EU courts just made it crystal clear that algorithmic transparency isn&amp;rsquo;t optional - it&amp;rsquo;s mandatory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-eu-court-just-raised-the-stakes"&gt;The EU Court Just Raised the Stakes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In a landmark judgment (&lt;a href="https://curia.europa.eu/juris/document/document.jsf?text=&amp;amp;docid=295841&amp;amp;pageIndex=0&amp;amp;doclang=EN&amp;amp;mode=lst&amp;amp;dir=&amp;amp;occ=first&amp;amp;part=1&amp;amp;cid=15436379"&gt;Case C‑203/22&lt;/a&gt;) delivered on February 27, 2025, the Court of Justice of the European Union (CJEU) has provided crucial clarity on what companies must disclose when they use automated decision-making systems.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Modernizing Penetration Testing Reports: The Case for Standardization</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2025 08:18:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/12/modernizing-penetration-testing-reports-the-case-for-standardization/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In an era where cyber threats evolve at lightning speed, it&amp;rsquo;s puzzling that many organizations still handle penetration testing reports like they did two decades ago. The current process is a familiar dance: consultants meticulously document their findings in Word documents, convert them to PDFs, email them to clients, who then manually copy and paste the data into their issue tracking systems. This inefficient workflow isn&amp;rsquo;t just outdated—it&amp;rsquo;s actively hindering our industry&amp;rsquo;s ability to respond to security threats effectively.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Reminder #1</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</link><pubDate>Thu, 30 Jan 2025 19:59:39 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/01/30/reminder-1/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Distributed system&lt;/em&gt; is a characteristic of the deployment model, not of the code organization model.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>INTELLECT-1: A Groundbreaking Open-Source AI Model</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</link><pubDate>Sat, 30 Nov 2024 08:11:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/11/30/intellect-1-a-groundbreaking-open-source-ai-model/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Exciting news in the AI community!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://huggingface.co/lmstudio-community/INTELLECT-1-Instruct-GGUF"&gt;INTELLECT-1&lt;/a&gt;, developed by Prime Intellect with Arcee AI, represents a remarkable achievement in collaborative innovation. This fully open-source model stands out by transparently sharing its entire development process, from dataset to algorithms.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively created through distributed computing across 30 contributors from 5 countries, INTELLECT-1 isn&amp;rsquo;t just another fine-tuned model—it&amp;rsquo;s a fresh, ground-up approach that promises unique capabilities. Check out this pioneering project and support its innovative spirit!&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Maximizing Developer Productivity: Beyond the Code</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the fast-paced tech industry, the key to maximizing developer productivity lies not just in the code they write but in the culture and communication that surrounds them. It’s a dynamic process that requires more than just technical prowess; it requires a shift in mindset and approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the development process has been viewed as a straightforward transaction: management dictates what to build, and developers execute. However, this method can lead to inefficiencies, misinterpretations, and a heavy burden on the managerial layer, already strained with decision-making responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Creating an AI Plugin for Microsoft D365</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/29/creating-an-ai-plugin-for-microsoft-d365/</link><pubDate>Mon, 29 May 2023 07:16:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/29/creating-an-ai-plugin-for-microsoft-d365/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;This guide provides an overview of how to create an AI plugin for Microsoft Dynamics 365 and Azure, following the same standard as OpenAI&amp;rsquo;s ChatGPT plugins. This plugin enables users to interact with your product&amp;rsquo;s APIs through Copilot, access a knowledge base, and perform actions on behalf of the user.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="pre-requisites"&gt;Pre-requisites&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To create the plugin, your API&amp;rsquo;s domain must contain a folder named &lt;code&gt;.well-known&lt;/code&gt;. For example, &lt;code&gt;contoso.com/.well-known/&lt;/code&gt;. Without this folder, you cannot install the plugin.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Overcoming Anxiety: A Developer's Guide to Stress-Free Coding</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 May 2023 20:18:22 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/05/02/overcoming-anxiety-a-developers-guide-to-stress-free-coding/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you a software developer struggling with stress and anxiety? You&amp;rsquo;re not alone. As a former developer who battled panic attacks and burnout, I understand firsthand the challenges that come with the job. But I&amp;rsquo;m here to tell you that it doesn&amp;rsquo;t have to be this way.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Through small, positive changes in my daily routine, I was able to overcome anxiety and become a better developer, husband, and friend. It wasn&amp;rsquo;t an easy road, but it was worth it. And I want to help you do the same.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Embrace Your Personal Brand and Thrive in the AI Revolution</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/08/embrace-your-personal-brand-and-thrive-in-the-ai-revolution/</link><pubDate>Sat, 08 Apr 2023 14:06:25 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/04/08/embrace-your-personal-brand-and-thrive-in-the-ai-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;As we look forward to the rapid advancements of artificial intelligence (AI) in the coming years, it&amp;rsquo;s time to embrace the potential this holds for each of us. With AI technologies on the verge of making it possible to create SaaS and mobile applications without any technical expertise, we&amp;rsquo;ll soon see a significant shift in the way businesses are built and operated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Picture this: influencers will have the power to launch their own companies virtually overnight, without needing a development team. This monumental change will level the playing field, allowing anyone with a strong personal brand to dive headfirst into the entrepreneurial world.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Nocode: A Career Killer</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/22/nocode-a-career-killer/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2023 22:11:47 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/22/nocode-a-career-killer/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Nocode is the latest trend in the tech world, allowing anyone to create websites and apps without any coding knowledge. It&amp;rsquo;s a fun hobby that can lead to impressive results, but it could also be a career killer. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore why nocode is both loved and feared by professionals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-fun-hobby-that-could-ruin-you"&gt;The Fun Hobby That Could Ruin You&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nocode platforms like Webflow, Bubble, and Glide have made it easier than ever to build websites and apps. You can drag and drop elements, customize templates, and even add complex features like databases and user authentication. It&amp;rsquo;s a great way to experiment with new ideas and showcase your creativity.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Yerkes-Dodson's Law: Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/yerkes-dodsons-law-why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Do you find yourself either stressing out or being lazy all the time? Well, according to Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law, both of these behaviors can have negative consequences on your productivity and overall well-being. In this article, we&amp;rsquo;ll explore the science behind this law and explain why it&amp;rsquo;s important to find a balance between stress and laziness.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="why-stress-and-laziness-are-equally-bad-yerkes-dodsons-law-explained"&gt;Why Stress and Laziness are Equally Bad: Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law Explained&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yerkes-Dodson&amp;rsquo;s Law is a psychological principle that explains the relationship between stress and performance. Essentially, the law states that there is an optimal level of stress that leads to peak performance, but too much or too little stress can actually hinder productivity. This means that both too much stress and too much relaxation can be detrimental to your success.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Zakaj stres ni vedno slaba stvar? Yerkes-Dodsonov zakon: ELI5</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</link><pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/13/zakaj-stres-ni-vedno-slaba-stvar-yerkes-dodsonov-zakon-eli5/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Stres pogosto velja za sovražnika produktivnosti in sreče. Kaj pa, če vam povemo, da stres ni vedno slaba stvar? V skladu z Yerkes-Dodsonovim zakonom je lahko malo stresa dejansko koristno. Preden se prestrašite zaradi prihajajočega roka ali predstavitve, preberite, zakaj je stres morda vendarle vaš prijatelj.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="ste-pod-stresom-ne-prestrašite-se-še"&gt;Ste pod stresom? Ne prestrašite se&amp;hellip; še!&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vsi smo se že kdaj srečali s prepotenimi dlanmi, pospešenim bitjem srca in strahovitim občutkom strahu, ki se pojavijo ob stresu. Toda preden posežete po Xanaxu, upoštevajte naslednje: malo stresa lahko dejansko izboljša vašo učinkovitost. Res je, stres vas lahko motivira, saj vam pomaga, da se osredotočite in ostanete budni. Težava nastane šele, ko stres postane preobsežen in kroničen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Chill Out, Focus Right: Winning Equation for Software Success</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/chill-out-focus-right-winning-equation-for-software-success/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Software development is a complex and demanding field that requires a lot of focus and attention to detail. However, many developers often forget that taking a break and relaxing is just as important as working hard. In this article, we will explore the winning equation for software success, which involves chilling out and focusing right.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="chill-out-the-secret-ingredient-to-software-success"&gt;Chill Out: The Secret Ingredient to Software Success&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chilling out is not just a luxury, but a necessity for software developers. Taking a break from work can help you clear your mind, reduce stress, and increase creativity. When you are relaxed, you are more likely to come up with innovative solutions to complex problems. So, the next time you feel stuck, take a break and do something that makes you happy, whether it&amp;rsquo;s going for a walk, listening to music, or playing video games.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Umiri se, osredotoči se pravilno: zmagovalna enačba za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Razvoj programske opreme je lahko stresno in zahtevno področje. Z natančnimi roki, kompleksno kodo in nenehno spreminjajočimi se tehnologijami je enostavno postati preobremenjen in izgubiti osredotočenost. Vendar sta sproščen način razmišljanja in jasna osredotočenost ključna za doseganje uspeha pri razvoju programske opreme. V tem članku bomo raziskali zmagovalno enačbo za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme: umiri se in osredotoči se pravilno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="umiri-se-uspeh-pri-razvoju-programske-opreme-se-začne-s-sproščenim-razmišljanjem"&gt;Umiri se: Uspeh pri razvoju programske opreme se začne s sproščenim razmišljanjem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ko si pod stresom, tvoj možgani preidejo v način preživetja in tvoja sposobnost kreativnega razmišljanja in reševanja problemov upade. Zato je ključno gojiti sproščen način razmišljanja pri delu na projektih programske opreme. Redni odmori, vadba zavedanja in ukvarjanje z dejavnostmi, ki ti prinašajo veselje, ti lahko pomagajo, da ostaneš miren in osredotočen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>