<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Development on Digitaliziran</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/development/</link><description>Recent content in Development on Digitaliziran</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:14:50 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/tags/development/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Why Your Business Needs AI Agents Now: The n8n Revolution That's Changing Everything</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/why-your-business-needs-ai-agents-now-the-n8n-revolution-thats-changing-everything/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 14:14:50 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/24/why-your-business-needs-ai-agents-now-the-n8n-revolution-thats-changing-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still manually handling tasks that your competitors are automating with intelligent &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt;? While you&amp;rsquo;re drowning in repetitive workflows, forward-thinking businesses are deploying AI agents that think, decide, and act autonomously - and they&amp;rsquo;re doing it faster than ever with platforms like &lt;a href="https://n8n.io/"&gt;n8n&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-agent-reality-check"&gt;The AI Agent Reality Check&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://medium.com/superstringtheory/knowledge-brain-skills-how-to-make-useful-ai-agents-fast-24e570e0d560"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; aren&amp;rsquo;t just chatbots with fancy names. These are autonomous systems that can &lt;a href="https://medium.com/superstringtheory/knowledge-brain-skills-how-to-make-useful-ai-agents-fast-24e570e0d560"&gt;perceive their environment, make decisions, and take actions&lt;/a&gt; without constant human supervision. Think of them as digital employees who can analyze data, book meetings, manage customer inquiries, and even troubleshoot technical issues - all while you focus on strategic initiatives.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why Your AI Startup Needs Aviation-Grade Regulation: Lessons from 100 Years of Flight Safety</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Sep 2025 11:57:35 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/19/why-your-ai-startup-needs-aviation-grade-regulation-lessons-from-100-years-of-flight-safety/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you building your AI startup without considering the regulatory framework that could make or break your venture? While entrepreneurs rush to deploy the latest artificial intelligence solutions, the smartest founders are looking to an unexpected mentor: the aviation industry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-striking-parallels-you-cant-ignore"&gt;The Striking Parallels You Can&amp;rsquo;t Ignore&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just as aviation transformed from experimental flights to a trillion-dollar industry through rigorous safety standards, AI is following a remarkably similar trajectory. Both industries share three critical characteristics that suggest valuable regulatory lessons, though important differences must be acknowledged:&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your LLM Servers Are Exposed: Cisco's Shodan Study Reveals Critical Security Gaps</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/05/your-llm-servers-are-exposed-ciscos-shodan-study-reveals-critical-security-gaps/</link><pubDate>Fri, 05 Sep 2025 16:40:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/05/your-llm-servers-are-exposed-ciscos-shodan-study-reveals-critical-security-gaps/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your organization&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Large_language_model"&gt;Large Language Model (LLM)&lt;/a&gt; servers broadcasting sensitive information to the entire internet? A new &lt;a href="https://blogs.cisco.com/security/detecting-exposed-llm-servers-shodan-case-study-on-ollama"&gt;Cisco security study&lt;/a&gt; using &lt;a href="https://www.shodan.io/"&gt;Shodan search engine&lt;/a&gt; data reveals a troubling reality: thousands of &lt;a href="https://ollama.ai/"&gt;Ollama&lt;/a&gt; LLM servers are running with misconfigured settings, creating potential entry points for attackers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-scale-of-exposure"&gt;The Scale of Exposure&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cisco&amp;rsquo;s research team discovered numerous Ollama servers - a popular platform for running LLMs locally - exposed to the internet without proper security controls. However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to understand that &lt;strong&gt;Ollama is designed with secure defaults&lt;/strong&gt;. By default, &lt;a href="https://github.com/ollama/ollama/issues/11941"&gt;Ollama binds only to localhost (127.0.0.1)&lt;/a&gt;, restricting access to the local machine only. The exposures identified by Cisco&amp;rsquo;s research occur when administrators deliberately override these secure defaults by setting the &lt;code&gt;OLLAMA_HOST&lt;/code&gt; environment variable to &lt;code&gt;0.0.0.0&lt;/code&gt; to enable remote access, but fail to implement proper security measures.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are You Ready for Your Robot Teammate? The Rise of Human-Robot Collaboration in the Modern Workplace</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/02/are-you-ready-for-your-robot-teammate-the-rise-of-human-robot-collaboration-in-the-modern-workplace/</link><pubDate>Tue, 02 Sep 2025 18:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/09/02/are-you-ready-for-your-robot-teammate-the-rise-of-human-robot-collaboration-in-the-modern-workplace/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Picture this: You walk into your office tomorrow and meet your new colleague - a &lt;a href="https://www.epicor.com/en-us/blog/technology-and-data/the-role-of-cobots-in-enhancing-workplace-safety/"&gt;collaborative robot&lt;/a&gt;, or &amp;ldquo;cobot,&amp;rdquo; designed to work alongside you. This isn&amp;rsquo;t science fiction; it&amp;rsquo;s the reality of &lt;a href="https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S1877050924003223"&gt;Industry 5.0&lt;/a&gt;, where human-robot collaboration is transforming workplaces across manufacturing, healthcare, and service industries.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-shift-from-automation-to-collaboration"&gt;The Shift from Automation to Collaboration&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.osha.gov/robotics"&gt;industrial robots&lt;/a&gt; confined behind safety barriers, &lt;strong&gt;collaborative robots (cobots)&lt;/strong&gt; are engineered to work in shared spaces with humans. According to recent research from &lt;a href="https://asmedigitalcollection.asme.org/computingengineering/article/25/5/050301/1213609/Special-Issue-Human-Robot-Collaboration-in"&gt;ASME Digital Collection&lt;/a&gt;, the proper design of individual and joint tasks for humans and cobots can maximize collaborative potential, creating more efficient and adaptable work environments.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Guardrails Just Got Outsmarted by Emojis: The Semantic Prompt Injection Crisis</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</link><pubDate>Sun, 03 Aug 2025 09:17:44 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/08/03/your-ai-guardrails-just-got-outsmarted-by-emojis-the-semantic-prompt-injection-crisis/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are your AI systems as secure as you think? Recent research from &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s AI Red Team&lt;/a&gt; reveals a concerning reality: attackers can now bypass some AI guardrails using something as simple as emoji sequences and visual symbols.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-invisible-threat-in-plain-sight"&gt;The Invisible Threat in Plain Sight&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://www.paloaltonetworks.com/cyberpedia/what-is-a-prompt-injection-attack"&gt;Semantic prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; represent an emerging frontier in adversarial attacks against AI systems. Unlike traditional &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/think/topics/prompt-injection"&gt;prompt injections&lt;/a&gt; that rely on text manipulation, these attacks use symbolic visual inputs - emoji-like sequences, rebus puzzles, and other visual representations - to potentially compromise &lt;a href="https://developer.nvidia.com/blog/securing-agentic-ai-how-semantic-prompt-injections-bypass-ai-guardrails/"&gt;agentic AI systems&lt;/a&gt; while evading some detection methods.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Amazon's AI Assistant Nearly Wiped Developer Systems for 5 Days – Are Your Access Controls Ready?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</link><pubDate>Tue, 29 Jul 2025 19:14:46 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/29/amazons-ai-assistant-nearly-wiped-developer-systems-for-5-days-are-your-access-controls-ready/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Picture this scenario:&lt;/strong&gt; You&amp;rsquo;re working late, relying on your trusted &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/AI-assisted_programming"&gt;AI coding assistant&lt;/a&gt; to help debug a critical application. Unknown to you, that same assistant has been compromised and is quietly preparing to execute commands that could wipe your entire development environment – both local files and cloud infrastructure.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn&amp;rsquo;t a hypothetical nightmare. It actually happened to &lt;a href="https://aws.amazon.com/q/developer/"&gt;Amazon Q Developer Extension&lt;/a&gt; users for five consecutive days, and the implications should make every &lt;a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chief_information_security_officer"&gt;Chief Information Security Officer (CISO)&lt;/a&gt; reassess their AI integration strategies immediately.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Business Ready for Europe's AI Language Revolution? Microsoft's Bold Move Could Leave You Behind</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Jul 2025 08:16:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/22/is-your-business-ready-for-europes-ai-language-revolution-microsofts-bold-move-could-leave-you-behind/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;When was the last time you considered whether your AI tools truly understand your customers&amp;rsquo; native languages? If you&amp;rsquo;re operating in Europe&amp;rsquo;s diverse linguistic landscape, Microsoft&amp;rsquo;s latest announcement should make you pause and reassess your digital strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-wake-up-call-europe-needed"&gt;The Wake-Up Call Europe Needed&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Microsoft recently launched two initiatives that could reshape how AI serves Europe&amp;rsquo;s 200+ languages, though the impact may be more incremental than revolutionary. The tech giant&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href="https://blogs.microsoft.com/on-the-issues/2025/07/20/eudigitalunlock/"&gt;European Digital Unlock program&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t just another corporate initiative - it&amp;rsquo;s a direct response to a critical gap that&amp;rsquo;s been undermining European businesses for years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Your AI Procurement Strategy Could Be Your Biggest Compliance Risk: What Financial Services Must Know</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</link><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jul 2025 15:15:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/07/01/your-ai-procurement-strategy-could-be-your-biggest-compliance-risk-what-financial-services-must-know/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to procure AI solutions for your financial services firm without considering the legal minefield you&amp;rsquo;re entering? While competitors scramble to deploy the latest AI tools, smart institutions are discovering that &lt;strong&gt;procurement strategy - not just implementation - determines compliance success&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-procurement-blind-spot-thats-costing-millions"&gt;The Procurement Blind Spot That&amp;rsquo;s Costing Millions&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most financial institutions approach AI procurement like any other technology purchase. This is a critical mistake. Unlike traditional software, AI systems in financial services must navigate an intricate web of regulations including the &lt;a href="https://gdpr.eu/what-is-gdpr/"&gt;General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR)&lt;/a&gt; - the EU&amp;rsquo;s comprehensive data privacy law that governs how personal information must be handled - &lt;a href="https://www.eiopa.europa.eu/digital-operational-resilience-act-dora_en"&gt;Digital Operational Resilience Act (DORA)&lt;/a&gt; - a new EU regulation requiring financial institutions to strengthen their digital resilience against cyber threats - and emerging &lt;a href="https://artificialintelligenceact.eu/"&gt;AI-specific legislation&lt;/a&gt; like the EU AI Act.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>MCP's Hidden Security Crisis: Why Your AI Automation Strategy Needs an Urgent Reality Check</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</link><pubDate>Tue, 24 Jun 2025 16:33:37 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/24/mcps-hidden-security-crisis-why-your-ai-automation-strategy-needs-an-urgent-reality-check/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you rushing to implement &lt;a href="https://www.anthropic.com/news/model-context-protocol"&gt;Model Context Protocol (MCP)&lt;/a&gt; for your AI automation workflows? Before you do, consider this sobering reality: &lt;a href="https://blog.sshh.io/p/everything-wrong-with-mcp"&gt;MCP may be creating more security vulnerabilities than it solves&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;The Promise vs. The Reality&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://modelcontextprotocol.io/specification/2025-06-18"&gt;MCP&lt;/a&gt; promises seamless integration between &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/large-language-models"&gt;Large Language Models (LLMs)&lt;/a&gt; and third-party tools, positioning itself as the standard for AI-driven automation. Companies are adopting it to streamline workflows, reduce manual processes, and give &lt;a href="https://www.ibm.com/topics/ai-agents"&gt;AI agents&lt;/a&gt; unprecedented control over business operations.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Why n8n's $7.2M Revenue Growth Should Make Every Business Leader Rethink Workflow Automation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/why-n8ns-7-2m-revenue-growth-should-make-every-business-leader-rethink-workflow-automation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 18:19:33 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/why-n8ns-7-2m-revenue-growth-should-make-every-business-leader-rethink-workflow-automation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still manually juggling repetitive tasks while your competitors automate their way to efficiency? The explosive growth of n8n, a &lt;a href="https://www.atlassian.com/agile/project-management/workflow-automation"&gt;workflow automation platform&lt;/a&gt; that hit &lt;a href="https://getlatka.com/companies/n8nio"&gt;$7.2 million in revenue in 2024&lt;/a&gt; with just 59 employees, signals a fundamental shift in how businesses approach operational efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For those new to the concept, &lt;a href="https://zapier.com/blog/workflow-automation/"&gt;workflow automation&lt;/a&gt; is the process of streamlining and automating repetitive business tasks using software, allowing teams to focus on more strategic work.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Switzerland's Fintech Revolution: Are You Missing Europe's Most Crypto-Friendly Business Hub?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</link><pubDate>Mon, 23 Jun 2025 09:46:26 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/23/switzerlands-fintech-revolution-are-you-missing-europes-most-crypto-friendly-business-hub/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still navigating the complex maze of European &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/f/fintech.asp"&gt;fintech&lt;/a&gt; regulations while your competitors establish operations in Switzerland? While the European Union continues to wrestle with comprehensive &lt;a href="https://www.investopedia.com/terms/c/cryptocurrency.asp"&gt;crypto&lt;/a&gt; frameworks, Switzerland has quietly positioned itself as the continent&amp;rsquo;s most fintech-friendly jurisdiction.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;However, it&amp;rsquo;s important to recognize that the European fintech landscape is rapidly evolving, with multiple jurisdictions now competing to attract innovation. Countries like the &lt;a href="https://www.fca.org.uk/firms/innovation"&gt;United Kingdom&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href="https://www.bafin.de/EN/Aufsicht/FinTech/fintech_node_en.html"&gt;Germany&lt;/a&gt; have implemented robust &lt;a href="https://www.planetcompliance.com/compliance-software/innovation-hubs-v-regulatory-sandboxes-and-the-future-of-innovation-facilitators/"&gt;regulatory sandboxes&lt;/a&gt; and innovation hubs that provide fintech companies with controlled environments to test new products without full regulatory compliance burdens.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Are Your IT Audits Ready for the AI Revolution? Five Game-Changing Applications You Can't Ignore</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</link><pubDate>Fri, 06 Jun 2025 10:12:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/06/are-your-it-audits-ready-for-the-ai-revolution-five-game-changing-applications-you-cant-ignore/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still conducting IT audits the traditional way while your competitors leverage artificial intelligence to uncover risks you might miss? A recent &lt;a href="https://www.isaca.org/resources/news-and-trends/isaca-now-blog/2025/five-ways-that-it-auditors-can-put-ai-to-good-use"&gt;ISACA analysis&lt;/a&gt; reveals five transformative applications of AI in IT auditing that could revolutionize how you approach risk assessment and compliance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-ai-audit-advantage-beyond-human-limitations"&gt;The AI Audit Advantage: Beyond Human Limitations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditional auditing methods, while thorough, face inherent constraints: time limitations, human error, and the sheer volume of data in modern organizations. AI transforms these challenges into opportunities through &lt;strong&gt;risk analysis automation&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;intelligent evidence collection&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;continuous controls testing&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;real-time assurance monitoring&lt;/strong&gt;, and &lt;strong&gt;comprehensive process automation&lt;/strong&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Is Your Enterprise Database Strategy Ready for the Foundation Model Revolution?</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</link><pubDate>Thu, 05 Jun 2025 10:13:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/06/05/is-your-enterprise-database-strategy-ready-for-the-foundation-model-revolution/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Are you still moving data to AI algorithms instead of bringing AI to your data? &lt;a href="https://kumo.ai/company/news/kumo-relational-foundation-model/"&gt;Kumo AI&amp;rsquo;s KumoRFM&lt;/a&gt; shows a fundamental shift that could reshape how enterprises handle their most valuable asset: structured data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="the-game-changing-approach"&gt;The Game-Changing Approach&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;KumoRFM represents the first Relational Foundation Model (RFM) designed specifically for structured and relational data. Unlike traditional AI models that require extensive task-specific training and costly data migration, KumoRFM leverages &lt;strong&gt;in-context learning&lt;/strong&gt; to deliver accurate predictions across diverse databases without retraining.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Model Context Protocol: A Security Threat Masquerading as Innovation</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</link><pubDate>Mon, 14 Apr 2025 19:40:38 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/04/14/model-context-protocol-a-security-threat-masquerading-as-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;The tech world is abuzz with discussions about the Model Context Protocol (MCP), but security experts are raising red flags that should concern every organization considering its implementation. Far from being the revolutionary protocol its proponents claim, MCP may represent a significant security vulnerability that could compromise sensitive data and systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;MCP purports to facilitate communication between language models and external tools, creating a standardized way for AI systems to access data sources and execute functions. However, as detailed in a recent analysis, this so-called &amp;ldquo;protocol&amp;rdquo; is more accurately described as a scheme that lacks fundamental security safeguards.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Adventures in Setting Up NVIDIA's GH200 Grace Hopper: A Tale of Two Systems</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</link><pubDate>Mon, 10 Feb 2025 18:01:43 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2025/02/10/adventures-in-setting-up-nvidias-gh200-grace-hopper-a-tale-of-two-systems/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Today, I had the exciting opportunity to set up one of NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s most powerful AI computing platforms - the Grace Hopper Superchip (GH200). What makes this setup particularly interesting is that it&amp;rsquo;s actually two systems in one: the main Grace Hopper CPU-GPU system and the BlueField-3 DPU (Data Processing Unit).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="understanding-the-hardware"&gt;Understanding the Hardware&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The GH200 combines NVIDIA&amp;rsquo;s Grace CPU with a Hopper GPU architecture, creating a powerhouse for AI and high-performance computing workloads. The BlueField-3 DPU is essentially a network card on steroids - it&amp;rsquo;s a specialized processor that handles networking, storage, and security tasks, freeing up the main system for computational work.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Unexpected WCF Service Failure: The Hidden Impact of Dormant Monitoring Tools</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/07/19/unexpected-wcf-service-failure-the-hidden-impact-of-dormant-monitoring-tools/</link><pubDate>Fri, 19 Jul 2024 10:52:51 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/07/19/unexpected-wcf-service-failure-the-hidden-impact-of-dormant-monitoring-tools/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Last weekend, we encountered a perplexing issue with our WCF services that highlighted an important lesson about the long-term effects of unused software on our systems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Problem:
Our WCF services suddenly stopped functioning correctly, returning the following error message:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;code&gt;The exception message is 'A property with the name 'UriTemplateMatchResults' already exists.'. See server logs for more details.&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This error occurred on all environments where Instana, a monitoring tool, had been installed, despite the fact that it had been switched off for several years.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Maximizing Developer Productivity: Beyond the Code</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 08:03:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2024/01/24/maximizing-developer-productivity-beyond-the-code/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;In the fast-paced tech industry, the key to maximizing developer productivity lies not just in the code they write but in the culture and communication that surrounds them. It’s a dynamic process that requires more than just technical prowess; it requires a shift in mindset and approach.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Traditionally, the development process has been viewed as a straightforward transaction: management dictates what to build, and developers execute. However, this method can lead to inefficiencies, misinterpretations, and a heavy burden on the managerial layer, already strained with decision-making responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Umiri se, osredotoči se pravilno: zmagovalna enačba za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme</title><link>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Mar 2023 10:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://cbuctok.github.io/digitaliziran.si/2023/03/08/umiri-se-osredotoci-se-pravilno-zmagovalna-enacba-za-uspeh-v-razvoju-programske-opreme/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;Razvoj programske opreme je lahko stresno in zahtevno področje. Z natančnimi roki, kompleksno kodo in nenehno spreminjajočimi se tehnologijami je enostavno postati preobremenjen in izgubiti osredotočenost. Vendar sta sproščen način razmišljanja in jasna osredotočenost ključna za doseganje uspeha pri razvoju programske opreme. V tem članku bomo raziskali zmagovalno enačbo za uspeh v razvoju programske opreme: umiri se in osredotoči se pravilno.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id="umiri-se-uspeh-pri-razvoju-programske-opreme-se-začne-s-sproščenim-razmišljanjem"&gt;Umiri se: Uspeh pri razvoju programske opreme se začne s sproščenim razmišljanjem&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ko si pod stresom, tvoj možgani preidejo v način preživetja in tvoja sposobnost kreativnega razmišljanja in reševanja problemov upade. Zato je ključno gojiti sproščen način razmišljanja pri delu na projektih programske opreme. Redni odmori, vadba zavedanja in ukvarjanje z dejavnostmi, ki ti prinašajo veselje, ti lahko pomagajo, da ostaneš miren in osredotočen.&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>